<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Joyful news from heaven, or, The last intelligence from our glorified Jesus above the stars wherein is infallibly recorded how the soul dieth in the body : also is discovered I. What is that which sleeps in the dust, II. The nature of its rest, III. The manner of its waking, IV. The mystery of the dispute between Christ and the woman of Samaria, as touching the true point of worship, clearly opened : wherein you have drawn up a divine charge against the teachers of the Baptists, with all other teachers publick and private, for counterfeiting the commission of the man Jesus, being therein convicted of spiritual high treason against Christ the great commissioner of heaven and earth : with a true relation of the kingdom of darkness, prepared for the cursed seed of Cain, world without end / written by John Reeve and Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
            <author>Reeve, John, 1608-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12611276</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12611276</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64389</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58338)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64389)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1534:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Joyful news from heaven, or, The last intelligence from our glorified Jesus above the stars wherein is infallibly recorded how the soul dieth in the body : also is discovered I. What is that which sleeps in the dust, II. The nature of its rest, III. The manner of its waking, IV. The mystery of the dispute between Christ and the woman of Samaria, as touching the true point of worship, clearly opened : wherein you have drawn up a divine charge against the teachers of the Baptists, with all other teachers publick and private, for counterfeiting the commission of the man Jesus, being therein convicted of spiritual high treason against Christ the great commissioner of heaven and earth : with a true relation of the kingdom of darkness, prepared for the cursed seed of Cain, world without end / written by John Reeve and Lodowick Muggleton ...</title>
                  <author>Reeve, John, 1608-1658.</author>
                  <author>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48, 7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.J. for Francis Cosinet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 12-13 misprinted 11-12.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect : pages stained with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Muggletonians.</term>
               <term>Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64389:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64389:1"/>
            <p>Joyful News from Heaven: OR, THE LAST INTELLIGENCE FROM OUR Glorified <hi>JESUS</hi> above the Stars: Wherein is infallibly recorded, <hi>How that the Soul dieth in the Body;</hi> Alſo is diſcovered,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>What is that which ſleeps in the duſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>The nature of its reſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>The maner of its waking.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>The myſtery of the Diſpute between Chriſt and the Woman of</hi> Samaria, <hi>as touching the true Point of Worſhip,</hi> clearly opened:</item>
               </list>
Wherein you have drawn up a Divine Charge againſt the Teachers of the BAPTISTS, With all other Teachers publick and private, for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the Commiſsion of the Man <hi>Jeſus,</hi> being therein convicted of Spiritual High Treaſon againſt Chriſt the Great Commiſsioner of Heaven and Earth: With a True Deſcription of the <hi>Kingdom of Glory,</hi> prepared onely for the Seed of <hi>Adam,</hi> that bleſſed Seed of Faith; and a True Relation of the <hi>Kingdom of Darkneſs,</hi> prepared for the curſed Seed of <hi>Cain,</hi> world without end.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> the laſt Commiſſionated Witneſſes and Prophets of that onely High, Immortal, Glorious God, Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. J.</hi> for <hi>Francis Coſinet</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Anchor &amp; Mariner</hi> in Tower-ſtreet, at Mincing-lane end. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:64389:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64389:2"/>
            <head>A Tranſcendent Spiritual Treatiſe</head>
            <p>Upon ſeveral heavenly Doctrines, from the holy ſpirit of the man Jeſus, the only true God, ſent unto all his elect as a token of his eternal love unto them, by the hand of his own Prophet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>img his laſt Meſſenger, and Witneſs, and forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the viſible appearing of the diſtinct perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God in power and great glory, in the clouds of Heaven, with his ten thouſands of perſonal Saints, to ſeparate between the elect world, and the reprobate world, to all Eternity: Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe ſeveral Heads ſet down in the next Page following.</p>
            <p>John Reeve <hi>and</hi> Lodowick Muggleton, <hi>the two laſt Witneſſes and true Prophets of the man Jeſus, the only Lord of Life and Glory, ſent by his holy Spirit to ſeal the foreheads of the Elect, and the foreheads of the rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obate, with the eternal Seals of Life and Death, and ſuddenly after we have delivered this dreadful Maſsage, this God the man Jeſus, will viſibly appear to bear witneſs whether he ſent us or not: ye that are the bleſſed ſhall patiently wait for the truth of this thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any of the Elect deſire to ſpeak with us concerning any thing written in this Treatiſe, they may hear of us in <hi>Great Trinity Lane,</hi> at the Chandlers Shop, againſt one Mr. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llis,</hi> a Brown Baker, near the lower end of <hi>Bow-lane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for the Author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and are to be ſold by them at the place above-named.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:64389:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64389:3"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Of my Commiſſion received by voyce of words from the ſpirit of the man Jeſus in glory.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Of the laſt great deceiving Antichrist, and man of ſin that ever ſhall be.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Of the unlawfulneſs for a ſpirituall Chriſtian to warre with a ſword of ſteel.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Of the creation beyond the ſtars, or of the other ſide of the viſible created heavens, were ſun, moon, and ſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſhall all vaniſh like ſmoak together to eternity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Of the creating of that reprobate Angel Serpent that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled Eve, and became a man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Of the eternal Creator cloathing himſelf with fleſh, and ſo bec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me a pure man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> and <hi>VIII.</hi> Of the creating of man, and the nature of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels in their creation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Of <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet aſcending bodily in heaven, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the perſon of God the Father.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Of all Prophets, or Prieſts, or Miniſters in this world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe, not knowing the true God; therefore not ſent by the God of all truth, the man Jeſus.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Of all heathen Magiſtrates, and their heathen Prophets, falſe worſhip or image.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Of the mortality of the ſoule, and how and when it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came mortal.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> With what bodies the elect and the reprobate ſhall appear after dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> How the bodies and ſpirits of the world of the elest be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſhall be like unto the glorious body of God their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, in his glory to eternity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> Of ſome difference between the glory of Men and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngels in glory in the heaven above.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64389:4"/>
            <p>AN Epiſtle from the holy Spirit of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the eternal Father, written by the Lords two laſt witneſſes and prophets, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall declare the mind of God the man Jeſus, that was crucified without the gates of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> the Lord Jeſus by us his poor deſpiſed meſſengers hath ſent this Writing unto the Chriſtian world ſo called. Wherefore we declare by vertue of our Commiſſion, given unto us by voice of words from the holy Spirit of the Lord Jeſus from the throne of his glory, to make known his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will and pleaſure both to the elect world, and reprobate world, a little before his glorious coming to ſeparate between the two worlds, that whoſoever deſpiſeth this Writing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be a King, or a Beggar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by calling it blaſphemy, or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, or deluſion, or a lye, or ſpeaking evil of it in any kind whatſoever; in ſo doing they have committed that unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt, or ſpirit that ſent us, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in obedience to our Commiſſion from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whom they have deſpiſed, and not us, we pronounce them curſed both ſoule and body from the preſence of the Lord Jeſus, elect men, and Angels, to all eternity.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Reeve</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> the Lords two laſt true Witneſſes and Prophets, ſpoken of in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of the Revelation, a little before the coming of him that ſent us, who is the Judge of both quick and dead.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64389:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <p> 
                  <hi>FEbruary</hi> the 3.4 and 5. 1651. three mornings together, much about an houre, the Lord Jeſus, the only wiſe God, whoſe glorious perſon is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident above or beyond the ſtars, I declare from the ſpirit of truth, that this Jeſus from the throne of his glory, by voice of words, ſpake unto me <hi>John Reeve,</hi> ſaying; I have given thee underſtanding of my mind in the Scriptures, above all men in the world. The next words the Lord ſpake unto me, were theſe, ſaying; Look into thy own body, there thou ſhalt ſee the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Kingdom of Hell: the Lord ſpake theſe words unto me twice together. Again, the Lord ſpake unto me theſe words, ſaying; I have choſen thee my laſt meſſenger for a great work, unto this bloudy unbeleeving world. And I have given thee <hi>Lodowick Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton</hi> to be thy mouth: at that very moment the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit brought inot my mind that Scripture of <hi>Aaron</hi> given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes.</hi> Again, the Lord ſpake unto me theſe words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; I have put the two-edged ſword of my ſpirit into thy mouth, that whoever I pronounce bleſſed, through thy mouth, is bleſſed to eternity; and whoever I pronounce cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through thy mouth, is curſed to eternity. When I heard theſe words, my ſpirit deſired the Lord, that I might not be his dreadfull meſſenger. For indeed I thought upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering of ſo ſad an unexpected meſſage unto men, I ſhould immediately have been torn to pieces. Again, the Lord ſpake unto me theſe words, ſaying; If thou doſt not obey my voyce, and go where ever I ſend thee to deliver my meſſage, thy body ſhall be thy hell, and thy ſpirit ſhall be the devill that ſhall torment thee to eternity; then for a moment I ſaw this hell within me, which cauſed me to anſwer the Lord theſe words, ſaying; Lord, I will go wherever thou ſendeſt me, only be with me. Theſe were the Lords words ſpoken unto me the firſt morning, and my anſwer unto my God; I being as perfectly awaked when he ſpake unto me, the Lord is my witneſſe, a <hi>I</hi> was at the writing hereof. Again, the next morning the Lord ſpake unto me, ſaying;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64389:5"/>Go thou unto <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> and with him go unto <hi>Thomas Turner,</hi> and he ſhall bring you to one <hi>John Tane,</hi> and do thou deliver my meſſage when thou comeſt there; and if <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> deny to go with thee, then do thou from me pronounce him curſed to eternity. Theſe words the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord ſpake unto me the ſecond morning, and no more. The third and laſt morning, the Lord ſpake unto me theſe words, ſaying; Goe thou unto <hi>Lodowick Muggle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and take ſuch a woman along with thee; and then go thou unto one <hi>John Robins,</hi> a Priſoner in new Bridewell, and do thou deliver my meſſage to him when thou comeſt there. Theſe were the Lords words the third and laſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and all the words in the Commiſſion of the Lord ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto me; only this meſſage of the Lod extends in general to the whole world; becauſe the elect Jewes and Gentiles are mixt in marriages through all parts of this Earth, for whoſe ſakes only we are ſent. But as for thoſe natural unbeleeving Jewes, that deny that God is come in fleſh, thoſe Jews ſhall never come to the faith of Jeſus, we are not ſent unto theſe. The holy Spirit beareth witneſſe in my ſpirit of the truth of that which I ſhall write unto you, that the firſt words that the Lord ſpake into me, the words ſpeaking came into my ſpirit and body, with ſuch an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bright burning glory of God like Majeſty, that I did not well know whether I was a mortal man, or an immortal God; ſo glorious are the words of the immortal God, that the tongues of Men nor Angels can never expreſſe it; my body alſo was changed at that time for a ſeaſon in a moſt dreadful manner to behold, of the which there be many can bear witneſs at this time. Again, for your information that are ſpirituall, the Lord opened the underſtanding of my fellow witneſſe, and made him obedient with me in the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the Lord, as <hi>Aaron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> underſtanding was opened, to make him obedient with <hi>Moſes</hi> in the meſſages of the Lord at that time; and the Lord hath given him as glorious te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies by Revelation from his holy ſpirit many a time of the full aſſurance of this Commiſſion to be from the Lord, as ever the Lord gave to <hi>Aaron</hi> to aſſure him, that <hi>Moſes</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64389:5"/>Commiſſion was from the Lord; onely <hi>Moſes</hi> Commiſſion (he being the Lords firſt Commiſſioner unto men) was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted by natural ſignes viſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y upon the bodies of men and women: and on the contrary; we being the Lords laſt Commiſſioners, our Commiſſion is manifeſted by ſpiritual ſignes, upon the inviſible ſpirits of men and women<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe our meſſage is all ſpiritual, concerning men and womens eternal weal or woe in the life to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <p>II. A Gaine, That you that are elected unto eternall Glory, may underſtand ſome thing of <hi>John Robins</hi> aforeſaid; I declare from the holy Spirit, that this <hi>John Robins</hi> was that laſt great Antichriſt, or man of ſin, or ſon of perdition, ſpoken of by <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle in the <hi>Theſſalouians,</hi> who (as it is written) oppoſeth, and exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God; ſo that he as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelfe that he is God: This is he that was to appeare in this laſt Age, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before the perſonall viſible coming of the Lord Jeſus in the Clouds, with his ten thouſands of Saints in power and great glory, to ſeparate between the perſons of the true Chriſtians, whoſe weapons are ſpiritual Faith, that worke by love and patience, with all other ſuch like heavenly vertues, from the perſons of all lying Hypocrites, who call themſelves Chriſtians, but they are indeed far worſe then Heathens, by killing their Neighbours with the ſword of ſteele; therefore their damnation will be far greater then the Heathens, in the day of the Lords vengeance. Againe, it would be too tedious to write unot you, wherein this <hi>John Robins</hi> did appear to be the man of ſin as before-ſaid; ſo that the <hi>Pope</hi> is not the man of ſin, as men blindly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for want of the ſpirit of the Scriptures: but on the contrary, I declare from the ſpirit of the Lord Jeſus, that all men that call themſelves Chriſtians, and yet make uſe of the ſword of ſteel, in any caſe whatſoever, the Pope and thoſe men are both Chriſtians alike; therefore to be an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, or a man of ſin to oppoſe God, as before ſaid, <hi>I</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare from the holy Spirit, that is, when a man doth exalt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64389:6"/>himſelf in the place or perſon of God, and doth ſet up a worſhip ſeemingly, far more pure then the ſimple plain wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and to manage his deſign, he doth ſhew many great lying ſigns and wonders, as this <hi>John Riobns</hi> did, to the amazement of many deceived by him. It was a ſpiritual op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Jeſus, which is the only God, by ſhewing of ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpiritual lying ſignes and wonders, as this <hi>John Robins</hi> did, yea, he ſhewed ſuch ſigns as the Popes could never ſhew, nor never ſhall ſhew: wherefore that you that are the elect, may no longer remain in the dark, concerning the laſt great ſpiritual Antichriſt, I declare from the Lord Jeſus that this <hi>Jo. Robins</hi> did attribute to himſelf the titles of the only God: firſt he called himſelf <hi>Adam, Melchizedeek:</hi> again, he call'd himſelfe the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Alſo, he held forth a Trinity of Perſons; as namely, <hi>Adam, Abel,</hi> and <hi>Cain:</hi> Again, he call'd himſelf the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying, after he had been five thouſand ſix hundred and odd years in the duſt, he was riſen from the dead to deliver his people; then he ſaid, that <hi>Abel</hi> was his Son Jeſus, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon of his Trinity: then he called <hi>Cain</hi> the Holy Ghoſt, and this was his third Perſon of his Trinity. This <hi>Cain</hi> that was the ſeed of the Serpent, or ſon of the Devil, this was his Holy Ghoſt. I could write very much of his Trinity concerning his Wife <hi>Eve</hi> ſo called by him, and of a Jeſus he ſaid ſhould be born of her of his begetting, and of a Diſciple of his that he called <hi>Cain,</hi> to make up his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Trinity, but that it would hinder things of more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue: again, he declared, that he knew all Angels, their names, and their natures; alſo he ſaid, he had a power over all voyces; alſo he ſaid, that he knew what the ſpirits of men ſpake that were in the duſt: againe, he ſaid, that he was Judge both of quick and dead; again he ſaid, that the Lord Jeſus was a weak and an imperfect Saviour, and afraid of death; but he ſaid, that he had no fear of death in him at all; but this <hi>Cain</hi> hath proved himſelf an old lyar, ſince his great blaſphemy againſt the Lord Jeſus: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, this <hi>John Robins</hi> did declare, that he was to gather the Jews in all Nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and to lead them into their own Land
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64389:6"/>unto <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> with many more ſuch like things declared by him.</p>
               <p>A for his lying ſpiritual ſignes and wonders, they were theſe and ſuch like, unto ſome that were deceived by him, he did preſent the form of his perſon riding, upon the wings of the Wind like unto a flame of fire; alſo he did preſent unto ſome in their beds a great light, like unto a flame of fire over all the Room, that they have been compell'd to hide their faces in their beds, fearing they ſhould be burn'd; but when they hid their faces in their bed, the light did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more brighter then before: alſo he would preſent unto them half Moons and Stars, and ſometimes thick darkneſſe, darker then any natural darkneſſe whatſoever: alſo he did preſent his head only in the day time without a body, to a Gentlewoman that <hi>I</hi> know in her Chamber; alſo preſenting unto her to deceive her, the forms of ſtrance beaſts, as namely Dragons, and ſuch like. Again, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare from the Lord, that this <hi>John Robins</hi> did preſent the form of his face, looking me in the face in my bed, the moſt part of a night, inſomuch that I cryed in my ſpirit unto the Lord, and the Lord by his Spirit revealed this great Antichriſt unto me, to my exceeding joy, and his everlaſting praiſe. Much more might be ſpoken of his deceits in this kind; but now I ſhall declare the manner of his being worſhipped as a God, by thoſe deceived by him: they prayd unto him, and they fell flat on their faces and worſhipped him, calling him their Lord and their God; alſo he gave commandment to ſome of them, that they ſhould not make mention of any other God, but him on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y: alſo he gave authority unto ſome of his Diſciples, both unto men, and women<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to change their wives and their husbands, telling them that they were not united to their own bone. This curſed <hi>Cain</hi> changed his own wife firſt, for an example, and called her name <hi>Eve,</hi> telling his Diſciples, that ſhe ſhould bring forth his Son Jeſus, and it ſhould be caught up into Heaven; many of his Diſciples following of his curſed example, to their utter ruine, in this life and that to come: a ſo he commanded his Diſciples to abſtain from meats
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64389:7"/>and drinks, promiſing them that they ſhould in a ſhort time be fed with Manna from Heaven, until many, a poor ſoul was almoſt ſtarved under his dyet, yea and ſome were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſtarved to death, whoſe bodies could not bear his diet; for thoſe that believed on him indeed, they brought in their whole eſtates unto him; ſo that then he had full power over their ſouls, and bodies, and eſtates, and he did plague their ſpirits and bodies at his pleaſure, in a moſt dreadful manner, if they were not obedient to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, of the which I my ſelf was an eye-witneſſe. I could ſpeak more of this Prince of Devils, in this laſt age; but I know I have written enough, for a ſpiritual Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>an to diſcern ſomething of this great Deceiver in what I have written: when his wickedneſſe was at the full, the Lord Jeſus ſent me as beforeſaid unto this <hi>John Robins</hi> to declare his wickedneſſe unto him, and immediately to pronounce him curſed in ſoul and body, from the preſence of the Lord Jeſus, to all eternity; unto the which I with my fellow witneſſe were made obedient; then about two months af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſentence of the Lord Jeſus, this <hi>John Robins</hi> wrote a Recantation of all his ſeeming great matters declared by him, and ſent the writing to General <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his liberty, when he was out of priſon, he gave all his diſciples about <hi>London</hi> the ſlip, and with what ſilver ſtead of building of Cities, he went into his own Country, and repurchaſed his Land, but it was re-bought with the innocent blood of many poor innocent ſouls, in the higheſt nature, that ever any man gained ſuch a ſum of ſilver as he did.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <p>III. A Gain, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that all thoſe that bear the name of Chriſtians, and yet make uſe of the ſword of ſteel to ſlay men, who are the image of God, they are utterly ignorant of the true God, and man Jeſus, and enemies to his Goſpel, that commands men to love their enemies; therefore their fleſhly reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſeth them to forſake the Goſpel of ſuffering the Groſſe of Chriſt, and they apply themſelves to the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to prove it lawful to kill the Goſpel of Jeſus, inſtead
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64389:7"/>of yielding obedience unto it. Unto you that are choſen to work righteouſneſſe, I declare by revelation from the Holy Spirit, that no ſpiritual Chriſtian hath any thing to do to meddle with any Scripture from the Law, given by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to prove it lawful to warre with the ſword of ſteel, becauſe it was lawful for the Nation of the Jews on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by commiſſion from the Lord, to warre againſt all the Heathen Gentiles that roſe up againſt the Jews, becauſe they worſhipped the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was contrary to the Heathen Idol-gods; and this war of the Jews was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful until God the Father became fleſh, to reconcile both Jew and Gentile into that one faith, in the body of his fleſh, and no longer: Therefore ſince God became fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, ſinne only excepted, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that they that are Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, they are not under the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is a Sword of ſteel, but they are under Grace, or the Goſpel of Jeſus, that is the ſword of the Holy Spirit, that makes all true Chriſtians to underſtand, that in this work their portions is to ſuffer all kind of wrong from all men, and to return mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and forgiveneſſe unto all men, yea and to forgive thoſe that would kill them, becauſe they know all vengeance is the Lords, and he will repay it; therefore they dare not rob God of his glory. Again when the Lord Jeſus gave that new Law of love unto all his elect believers, where he ſaith it was ſaid of old, an Eye for an Eye, and a Tooth for a Tooth; but I ſay unto you, love your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you. Theſe be thoſe Chriſtians indeed that may be called perfect; as their heavenly Father was perfect; the Lord Jeſus, who did all good, and ſuffered all wrong, yea, and laid down his life for that whole world of his Elect, when they were all become his enemies. Again, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that they that are new born by the Holy Spirit, they are ſo farre from killing, or conſenting to the killing of any man, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, or defenſively, in their own behalfe, or in the behalfe of any other man, that they are afraid of their own evill thoughts, and much more of evil words or deeds, againſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64389:8"/>God or men; becauſe they know nothing but pure righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, pure love without envy, and pure innocency ſhall raign in eternall glory with the only eternal Father, the Lord Jeſus; And on the contrary, they know all man-ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, under what pretence ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver, and all Govertous, Idolaters, Drunkards, Swearers, Lyers, Sorcerers, Whoremongers, and all thoſe that vindicate unrighteouſneſſe, through the love of ſilver, in oppoſing of that pure Law of love, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all Chriſtians not to do as they are done unto, that is the hypocrits righteouſneſſe: But on the contrary, to do unto all men, as you would they ſhould do unto you; this is the righteouſneſſe of pure faith, which is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, which makes men to fulfil all righteouſneſſe, for want of this, thoſe unrighteous perſons beforeſaid muſt all periſh to eternity. Again, I declare from the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that all thoſe that hate to yield obedience to this pure peaceable Law of love, proceeding from the pure ſpirit of the Lord Jeſus; I ſay in the great and notable day of the Lord, by his decree, or by a word ſpeaking from his mouth, they ſhall every one of them riſe out of the duſt together; not with the ſame bodies they died, or fell aſleep in, becauſe there was ſomewhat of God in thoſe bodies, whileſt they lived, which periſheth with them indeath; but the bodies which they ſhall have, ſhall be in forme of their former bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but they ſhall be fiery bodies, of ſpiritual darkneſſe, yea bodies of all unrighteouſneſſe, having all the inwicked deeds of their former bodies conveyed into theſe bodiers, as fewell to kindle the fire of new ſorrows: In theſe bodies of Hell and utter darkneſſe, and their ſpirits in their bodies ſhall be all fiery Devils; ſo their bodies ſhall be their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Hell, and their proud ſpirits, that had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe, ſhall be the Devils, that ſhall be barr'd in cloſe priſoners within their bodies, from all motioning or thinking of any former comforts, either ſpiritual, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, to give them any eaſe at all, becauſe all time is paſt; then as beforeſaid ſhall their ſpirits and bodies burn toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like a flame of fire, that is all as dark as pitch, they never ſtirring from the place of their reſurrection, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64389:8"/>ſeeing one anothers face<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> more, much leſſe ſhall they ſee the face of God, juſt men, or Angels, to all eternity, and the place of their eternall torment ſhall be upon this earth, where they acted all their bloodſhed, and all other unrighteouſneſs. Then ſhall the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and all other natural lights in this lower creation or world; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or go out like the ſnuff of a candle, giving no more light to eternity: then ſhall this fruitful pleaſant earth be like unto dry burning ſand, the ſeas and all rivers or ſprings of water being dryed up for evermore, as if they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any being: this whole creation being turned into a chaos of confuſion, without forme, and void of all light or ſap, either natural or ſpiritual, to all eternity, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>Again, I declare by Revelation from the Holy ſpirit, what was from Eternity, before any creature was formed, that had any ſenſible life, either in heaven above, or in this e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th beneath; there were theſe two uncreated ſubſtances of earth and water, with the uncreated ſpiritual perſon of God the Creator, in whoſe glorious prefence theſe ſenſeleſs ſubſtances of earth and water were eternally reſident, that the creator might create or forme by his infinite wiſedome out of thoſe dead ſubſtances, all variety of ſenſible living creatures in his own time, for the ſetting forth of his viſible glory to eternity. Again, I declare by Revelation from the holy ſpirit, that the earth and the water were both dark ſubſtances, having no light or ſenſible life at all in them, but the perſon of the creator was infinitely full of all glorious lights and ſenſible life to himſelf, both within and without. Thus it is clear there was death from eternity, only it was not in a ſenſible forme, as well as there was ſenſible life, light, and glory, in forme from eternity. Again, eternall life or God, was a ſubſtantial forme from eternity, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death or darkneſſe of earth and water was ſubſtance without forme, void of all ſpirit or life, ſo that life or ſpirit only is all ſubſtantiall forme, and death or darkneſſe only, is all ſubſtance without forme; ſo that life and death from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernity are not bare words, as blind hypocrites imagine, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64389:9"/>the inviſible creator of all life or ſpirits, was a God of a glorious ſubſtance, a ſpirituall body, in the form or likeneſſe of a man from all eternity. Again, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that the glorious ſenſible life or light in the perſon of the Creator, could not poſſibly be known by Men or Angels, but by his creating or forming of ſome creatures to live ſenſibly in death and darkneſſe, ſhame and miſery, and by his creating other creatures in oppoſition ſenſibly to live in life and light, joy and glory. Again, the infinite glorious prerogative power of the Creator, could not poſſibly be known to any of his creatures, to make a diſtinction between the glory of eternal life, and the miſery of eternal death; but by his forming of creatures of the ſame lump to be veſſels of honour and veſſels of diſhonour to eternity: but of the contrary, if the Creator without diſtinction had formed his creatures to be all eternally glorious like himſelf, then the glory of his prerogative power of infinite love or mercy, and infinite juſtice or wrath, and all his infinite new wiſdom increaſing or flowing in his glorious perſon as a fountain of living waters muſt in a manner have been ſhut priſoner in his own perſon, and the creatures muſt have been all as Gods, inſtead of creatures, and ſo the Creator would have had no glory in his Creation at all of the prerogative power of his Godhead. Wherefore I declare by vertue of my Commiſſion from the only wiſe God and everlaſting Father, the man Jeſus in glory, that all thoſe that are made to yield obedience in love to the prerogative power of God, are his Elect ones appointed for bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe to all Eternity; but on the contrary, all thoſe that are offended at the prerogative power of the Creator, and love to diſpute againſt it, are all Reprobates, and appointed to be curſed to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64389:9"/>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <p>IV. AGain, for your Information I declare from the holy ſpirit, that the Creation above or beyond the ſtarre of the holy Angels, who are ſpiritual bodies, in their perſons formed like men, and all other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that God hath made in the heavens above, of that ſubſtance of earth and water aforeſaid, that was from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, in the preſence of his eternal ſpiritual perſon, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that God the Creator hath made that creation in the heavens above, as viſible to be ſeen, as this creation is ſeen in this earth beneath. Again, <hi>I</hi> declare from the holy Spirit, that the glorious perſon of the onely wiſe God and eternal Father the Lord Jeſus, is as viſibly ſeen of the creatures, where his perſon is reſident, as a man is viſibly ſeen of the creatures in this earth beneath where his perſon reſides: as for this cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation in the heavens above, it is to ſet forth the glory of his immortal perſon, that all the creatures in his preſence viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beholding the glorious perſon of their Creator, both ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, and other creatures according to their wiſdom or underſtanding, might give him the glory of their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal happineſſe of this their creation: and on the contrary, if the Creator were not viſibly ſeen by the eyes of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then no creatures could poſſibly know him to return any praiſe or glory unto him at all, for the happineſs of their condition. Therefore it is a curſed lying imagination for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to think that the glorious perſon of God is not as viſibly ſeen of his creatures in the heavens above, as the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man, who is the image of God, is viſibly ſeen of the creatures in this earth beneath. Again, you muſt not think after a fleſhly manner, that the creatures above the ſtarrs are male and female for natural generation, as they are in this creation beneath the ſtarrs: for a woman had never been made but for generation, that the immortal God might have a womans womb in this world, to cloath himſelf with fleſh, and that the Reprobate Angel, which is the Devil, might have the womb of a woman to cloath himſelf with fleſh alſo, to bring forth Gods glorious deſign, between the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64389:10"/>ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent; wherefore I declare from the holy Spirit, that the holy Angels, and all other Creatures that are in the preſence of God in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beyond the ſtars, are all ſpiritual male creatures, never encreaſing in their numbers, not being fleſhly, deſiring gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but their ſpirits or natures, inſtead of fleſhly pleaſures in generation, are full of ſpiritual and heavenly joyes, of a more tranſcendent glorious content within themſelves, and viſible glorious contents in their beholding of the glorious face of God; and the faces of one another, and the glory of that place they enjoy, the which exceeding glory ſhineth forth through that heavenly Kingdom, from the bright burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glorious perſon of God the Creator, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who alone hath all the glory of his Creation in the Heavens above, wherein dwelleth nothing but righteouſneſſe in Glory.</p>
               <p>Again, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that no man can un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, or know any thing of theſe things that are inviſible unto our natural eyes, but by the Spirit of Revelation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is written, that faith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen: again, it is written, through faith we underſtand that the worlds were framed by the word of God; ſo that things which are ſeen were not made of things which do appear; ſo that in the Letter of the Scripture, it is clear to you that ſee by the eye of Faith, that God hath made or framed two Worlds, or two Creations which is all one; for you know to frame a thing, or to make a thing is all one. Again, unto you it is clear, there are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual viſible things, in that world above or beyond the ſtars, as well as here are natural viſible things in this world beneath the ſtars; becauſe you may underſtand that this world, and the things that are viſible therein, were made or created out of that world which is inviſible to us, who are in mortality, but viſible to thoſe who are above in glory; ſo that now, you that are appointed to enter with ſpiritual bodies into that glorious Creation, or world beyond the ſtars, may underſtand a little clearer of your inheritance in that Kingdome made without hands, or City eternal in the Heavens, where you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64389:10"/>ſhall viſibly ſee with your eyes the face of God, Men, Angels, and all Creatures, in that creation above the ſtars, as you ſee the face of man, and all other creatures in this creation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the ſtars, with glorious new Songs of ſpiritual and heavenly praiſes unto a glorious God, to all eternity. This proves the truth of theſe Scriptures, where it is written, <hi>My kingdom is not of this world:</hi> and of this ſaying, <hi>Lord remember me when thou comeſt into thy Kingdom:</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>In my Fathers Houſe,</hi> or Kingdom, <hi>are many manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>For thine is the Kingdom, the power, and the glory for ever:</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdoms of our Lord, and of his Chriſt:</hi> this world was the Heavens above; and of that ſaying, <hi>nevertheleſſe, we look for a new Heaven and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe,</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>He hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God, and we ſhall reign with him upon the Earth.</hi> This is that glorious new Heaven, and new Earth in the preſence of God, above or beyond the ſtars; but blind carnal hypocrites imagine, that Gods reigning with his Elect ones, will be upon this bloody Earth, becauſe they have no ſpiritual Eyes to ſee or know that new Heaven or new Earth, above or beyond the ſtars, where nothing but pure righteouſneſs reigneth in glory for everlaſting, or world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <p n="5">5. AGain, concerning that Serpent before-ſaid, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of the Lord for his ſubtilty; I declare by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation from the holy Spirit, that God created his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual perſon more glorious then the perſons of all the holy Angels that are in the preſence of God in Heaven, becauſe this mighty Angel, by the wiſdom and ſecret Counſel of God, was to be as a God, to bring forth his ſeed, or genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of wiſe, and prudent, ſubtile Serpent men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to oppoſe the Creator, and his innocent ſeed, or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſimple plain-hearted men and women, that are of the ſpirit of faith and pure love, with all other heavenly vertues; for the nature or Spirit of God, is faith and love, and all other divine vertues, infinitely living in his glorious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64389:11"/>Perſon, the which faith is all power of righteous actings, naturally flowing from his pure ſpirit, as from a pure over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing fountain of living waters: but on the contrary, the nature or ſpirit of this God-like Angel, and all the reſt of the holy Angels in their Creation, were pure reaſon, from whence naturally flows no good at all, but what comes into them continually by Revelation from that pure ſpirit of Faith, in the perſon of God their Creator; and this is that ſpiritual <hi>Manna</hi> that keeps the holy Angels natures or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits pure in the preſence of God; for it is the nature of that pure reaſon in the holy Angels continually to deſire the knowledge of that ſpirit of wiſdom in the Creator that made them, and the overflowings of that new wiſdom in the ſpirit of the Creator by the decree of God, it is that ſpiritual food that keeps the holy Angels pure in their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or elſe not one of them could ſtand upright in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, not one moment, but they would all become ſerpent-Devils, and fall down into this earth, as that great Angel did, preſently after the Lord withheld the revelation of his glorious wiſdom from him; then this Angel for want of his ſpiritual food of revelation, that kept his ſpirit in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Creator, preſently his ſpirit began proudly to imagine and think high and lofty thoughts concerning his own perſon, and great wiſdom of ſpirit within him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſecretly he was lifted up in his ſpirit to diſdain the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and wiſdom of all the holy Angels, in compariſon of the glory both of his perſon and wiſdom, pride being begun in him, <hi>Lucipher</hi>-like he ſoared higher in his pride, for he thought both his perſon and wiſdom to be as glorious, if not more glorious, then the perſon and wiſdom of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, wherefore he being very proud of his own wiſdom, he imagined that if he had been the Creator, he would by a word ſpeaking have created Angels, and all other creatures with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Water, as God made all things of; for his proud ſpirit thought he could by a word ſpeaking have crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all creatures of nothing at all, therefore he counted his wiſdom, rather greater, and of a more higher nature to have formed all things for a greater glory to himſelf, if he had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64389:11"/>been the Creator, then the Creators wiſdom in the things or Creatures formed by him; ſo imagining his wiſdom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Creators, he thought himſelf more fit to reign over the holy Angels, and all other creatures then the Creator; he being wiſe in his own conceit, became an abſolute Fool: for out of nothing comes nothing, and out of nothing comes no form, or nothing can be formed; for to create or make a living form or creature out of ſenſleſſe matter or ſubſtance, of Earth or Water, by a word ſpeaking, of what nature or form the Creator pleaſeth, whether contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his own nature and form, of his own nature and form, this is the power and wiſdom of my Creator, the Lord Jeſus; for he by his infinite glorious wiſdom, by a word ſpeaking did create all living creatures in the two Creations or Worlds, of unſenſible Earth and Water, that was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his perſon from all eternity in his preſence with him, becauſe his eternal glorious perſon you know, muſt have a place of reſidence, therefore reaſon it ſelf cannot deny the eternity of Earth and Waters, and the perſon of the Creator; let it imagine never ſo much, nor never ſo long: again, as beforeſaid, when the time of this proud and lofty Angels glory was by the decree of the Creator, expired in the Heavens above, to the exceeding joy of all the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, unto whom the Lord revealed his exceeding pride, the Lord then caſt down this Angelical wiſe Serpent into the Earth; therefore it is written, <hi>wo be to the Inhabiters of the Earth, for the Devil is come down amongſt you,</hi> this Angel that was caſt into the Earth, is that Devil beforeſaid, and his nature or ſpirit of pride and envy, and all other wickedneſſe being changed, his names or titles are changed according to the uncleanneſſe of his nature, and now inſtead of the name of an <hi>Angel of light,</hi> he is called an <hi>Angel of darkneſſe,</hi> as in <hi>Jude;</hi> yea he is called a <hi>Serpent,</hi> a <hi>Dragon,</hi> a <hi>Devil, Satan,</hi> or an <hi>unclean ſpirit,</hi> or <hi>that wicked one,</hi> ſuitable to his curſed nature; but the Lord changed not the form or perſon of this Reprobate loſt Angel at all, but his names or titles only as beforeſaid, according to his nature.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64389:12"/>
               <p>Again, I declare by Revelation from the Holy Spirit, that that Serpent ſpoken of in the Scripture that tempted the Virgin Wife <hi>Eve,</hi> he was a ſpiritual body in the form of his perſon like unto a man; yea, I ſay from the Lord, that this Angel-Serpent was more amiable or glorious in the form of his perſon to the outward appearance of <hi>Eves</hi> eyes, then the Perſon of the man <hi>Adam</hi> was; wherefore, by the prerogative power, and ſecret wiſdom and Counſel of God, to bring forth his glorious deſign, it was the outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the Serpents perſon, and his ſeeming wiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God-like counſel, by the decree of God, became a ſnare to deceive and overcome the innocent Virgin VVife <hi>Eve,</hi> as many a poor innocent Virgin in theſe dayes are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and overcome, by the outwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d comlineſſe of mens perſons, through their Serpent-counſels, and curſed temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; wherefore it is written, <hi>the woman was deceived, and not the man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, I declare by Revelation from the holy Spirit, that when this Angel-Serpent, by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeming wiſe God-like Counſel, had overcome innocent <hi>Eve,</hi> as before-ſaid; the very perſon of this ſpiritual Serpent Reprobate Angel, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the body or womb of innocent <hi>l ve,</hi> and there he dyed, or was changed from his ſpirituality, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he quickned in her pure undefiled ſeed, or nature all ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine luſt of all natural uncleanneſſe; wherefore, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now naked from her former pure created Virginity, preſently ſhe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> full of natural luſt after her innocent Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, that had no deſire to a woman at all, therefore it is written, <hi>and ſhe gave alſo unto her husband with her, and he did eat;</hi> then were they both naked, from that pure ſpiritual life of their virgin creation of God-l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke content within their own ſpirits, and in the room thereof they are both full of all natural luſts whatſoever; they being both defiled with the ſpirit of the Serpent-Angel of unclean reaſon and wicked imagination<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and this was that curſed effect of their becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as Gods, knowing both good an evil, until they were both born again by the ſpirit of Faith, to the full aſſurance of a more glorious Inheritance then that which was loſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64389:12"/>through the eternal love of God to his loſt Image.</p>
               <p>Again, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, that, that <hi>Cain</hi> that was the firſt born of <hi>Eve,</hi> he was the very ſeed or ſpirit of that reprobate Serpent angel in the body of <hi>Eve,</hi> and the firſt born child or ſon of the Devil, and ſo he became, and none but he alone, that <hi>Belzebub,</hi> the Prince of Devils, and the only father of all thoſe Angels of darkneſſe ſpoken of in the Epiſtle of <hi>Jude,</hi> that are kept or reſerved in chains of darkneſſe, of unbelief, unto the Judgment of the Great Day.</p>
               <p>Therefore, where it is written of the warfare between <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels, and the Dragon and his Angels, that <hi>Michael</hi> is the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus, in his Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal believers, whoſe ſpiritual weapons are faith, and love, and patience, and ſuch like, unto the death, becauſe they ſee a crown of Life, in yielding obedience to the croſſe of Chriſt. The Dragon, that is the ſpirit of curſed <hi>Cain</hi> in his perſecuting believers, whoſe carnal weapons are ſwords and guns, and all kinds of murdering weapons whatſoever, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ignorance, curſed covetouſneſſe, and vain-glorious envy, ſelling their eternal birthright for a meſſe of pottage, becauſe the Lord Jeſus hath no delight in their perſons. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it is written, <hi>and the Dragon was caſt out, that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent called the Devil and Satan,</hi> he was caſt out into the earth, and his Angels were caſt out with him; that <hi>Cain</hi> before-ſaid was that Serpent Dragon Angel, and his Angels are that fleſhly ſeed of his, or off-ſpring or generation of ſerpent, wiſe, prudent men and women that mind earthly things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Theſe are thoſe Serpent reprobate Angels, that go upon the bellies of their ſpirits, and lick up the duſt of the earth all the dayes of their lives: that is, their ſpirits lick up the gold and ſilver, and put it into a bag, for their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and this is the food of their ſouls, and ſuch like all their dayes. This is that ſpirit of unclean reaſon and wicked imagination that was in <hi>Cain,</hi> and now is in all his Angels, who are the Lords of this world, whoſe ſpirits wholly thirſt after things that periſh, and they are never in their proper center, but when the thoughts of their ſpirits are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64389:13"/>feeding upon riches, or honours, or friends, or fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, or long life, and ſuch like. This was the food of that Serpent <hi>Cain,</hi> that ſlew his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe he was more righteous then he; and this is the food and no other of all thoſe Serpent angelical men and women, both great and ſmall, that are the very ſons and daughters of curſed <hi>Cain,</hi> hating all ſpiritual righteouſneſſe in all ſpiritual <hi>Abels</hi> as he did. Therefore as beforeſaid, curſed together with that Serpent Reprobate Devil their father <hi>Cain,</hi> from the preſence of the Lord, juſt men and Angels, to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <p n="6">VI. AGain, for your Information, in whoſe perſons the Lord by his holy Spirit delights to dwell: I declare by Revelation from the holy Spirit of the Lord Jeſus, a little of that wonderful unſpeakable myſtery of God the Father, cloathing himſelf, or manifeſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in fleſh: it is written, <hi>ſhe was found with child by the Holy Ghoſt</hi> Again, it is written, <hi>for that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in her, is of the Holy Ghoſt; and the Word became fleſh; and behold a Virgin ſhall be with child, and ſhall bring forth a ſon, and they ſhall call his name</hi> Emanuel, <hi>which being interpreted, is God with us.</hi> Again, it is written, <hi>For unto us a child is born, unto us a ſon is given, and the government ſhall be on his ſhoulders, and his name ſhall be called Wonderful, Counſellor, the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace; of the increaſe of his government and peace there ſhall be no end:</hi> From theſe Scriptures, it is very clear in the bare Letter, unto you that ſee God by the eye of Faith, that that holy Child Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that was born of the Virgin-Wife <hi>Mary,</hi> he is the only God and alone eternal Father unto you that have faith in a perſonal God, or a God of one diſtinct perſon, and no more unto you alone, for whom is prepared a Crown of immortal glory. I declare by Revelation from the Holy Spirit of the Lord Jeſus, that the Holy Ghoſt beforeſaid, was the Glorious Perſon of that one only Wiſe God, and Everlaſting Father, and Creator of all things, that entred
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64389:13"/>into the Virgins womb, and dyed, or changed his immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality or ſpirituality in the body or womb of the Virgin, and immediately quickned or conceived himſelf of the very nature or ſeed of the Virgin; a pure natural child or ſon, in whom, as it is written, <hi>the fulneſſe of the God-head lived bodily;</hi> ſo that as the Serpet-angel beforeſaid, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the womb of the Virgin-VVife <hi>Eve,</hi> and defiled her pure nature, or ſeed throughout, and dyed in her womb from his ſpirituality, and quickned in mortality, and brought forth himſelf the firſt born child or ſon of the Devil, and ſo he became the father of an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of Serpent reprobate Devils of men and women; ſo in oppoſition of that reprobate Angel, and Prince of Devils beforeſaid, the glorious perſon of the eternal God entred into the womb of the Virgin-Wife <hi>Mary,</hi> and dyed in her womb from his immortality, and purified her nature or ſeed throughout, that was unclean before, and quickned himſelf in pure mortality, and brought forth himſelf the firſt born ſon of God, and the only eternal Father of an innumerable company of elect ſons and daughters purchaſed by his own precious blood: Thus immortality dyed and quickned in morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and this pure mortality dyed and quickned in immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and glory again, in that very ſame fleſh or perſon that dyed, and now reigneth in glory in the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and the loweſt hearts, God alone bleſſed to all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Thus Eternity became Time, and Time is become eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity again; for there is nothing but an eternal immortal God, that is the Creator of all life, that can by his own power, live and dye, and live again: But on the contrary, no creature hath any power at all, neither to live, nor to dye, but by the decree of the Creator alone, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Thus you that ſee by that ſingle eye of Faith, may underſtand in ſome meaſure the difference between the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent; for ever ſince the Angel-Serpent, by his wiſe curſed Counſel, took poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Garden of God, the bodies of our firſt parents.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64389:14"/>I declare from the Holy Spirit, that there is no Devil at all without the body of man or woman, but what dwells within the bodies of men and women; ſo that, that Devil ſo frequently ſpoken of in the letter of the Scripture, that tempts men and women to all unrighteouſneſſe, it is mans ſpirit of unclean reaſon, and curſed imagination, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiably luſteth after things that periſh; until the Holy Spirit of faith enters into the man, and purifies his unclean ſpirit, and reveals unto his dark underſtanding ſpiritual and glorious durable things, and that makes a man trample this periſhing world, and all its vain-glory, under the feet of his ſpirit as dung, as it is, in compariſon of the glory that is to come, in that world above the ſtars that remains to all eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <p n="7">VII. AGain, it is written, <hi>a woman ſhall compaſſe a man:</hi> that woman was the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and that man was God the Father. Again, it is written, <hi>a woman cloathed with the Sun, and the Moon under her feet, and upon her head a crown of twelve Stars:</hi> this woman was the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> beforeſaid, and the Sun that ſhe was cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed withal, was the only begotten Son of God, the eternal Father in the Virgins womb; and the Moon under her feet, that was the worſhip of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> for ſhe being cloathed with the Sun, ſhe was filled with the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the everlaſting Goſpel of that Son within her, which was of a more tranſcendent glory, than that of the Law: and that Crown of twelve Stars upon her head, that was the twelve Apoſtles that ſprang from her head Jeſus, to preach the everlaſting Goſpel of Truth and Peace unto his Elect: thus that ſaying, <hi>that every ſeed ſhall have his own body,</hi> is a little more clear unto you that have faith, in a perſonal God, then it was before: you may underſtand that God the Father was a ſpiritual man from eternity, and that in time his righteous ſpiritual body brought forth a righteous natural body, that the Father to ſhew forth his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64389:14"/>infinite love and humility, and to bring forth a new tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent glory to himſelf, might become a ſon, yea and a ſervant unto his creatures, in the very condition of a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a ſeaſon, that he might exalt his elect creatures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame condition of the Creator, in his glory in the higheſt Heavens to all eternity, when the curtains of this lower Heavens are drawn and vaniſht like ſmoak never more to be, time being paſt. Again, it is written, <hi>he that hath ſee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n me hath ſeen the Father, and the Father liveth in me, and I live in him, and I and the Father are one:</hi> the only mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or mind of the Lord Jeſus in thoſe words is this; his Spirit living within his body that was the Father, and his viſible body that was the Son, both God and man in one perſon, and ſo but one perſonal God, the man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, he perfectly knowing himſelf to be the only God, he ſaid unto the Jews, <hi>except ye eat my fleſh and drink my blood, you have no life in you:</hi> again he ſaid, <hi>except ye believe that I am he, ye ſhall dye in your ſins:</hi> his very mind in thoſe words was this, except they did believe, that that very perſon of his, of fleſh, blood, and bone that ſpake unto them, was the only God and eternal Father, and alone Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of all that were to be ſaved, and that there was no ſalvation to mankind, but thus ſpiritually eating of his fleſh, and drinking of his blood, except they did thus own his perſon, to be their Lord and only Saviour, they muſt all die in their ſins, and periſh to all eternity, becauſe there is nothing but the precious blood of a God, can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly clenſe the ſpirit of man from the power of ſin; therefore if the very Godhead had not died; that is, if the very ſoul of Chriſt (which is the eternal Father) had not died in the body, or with the body, to quiet or ſatisfie the cry of the guilt of ſin in mens ſpirits, all men would have periſht to eternity; becauſe the ſpirit of unclean rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Devil in man, whoſe nature is all ſin, did reign in the very bodies of the Elect, as their Lord and King, and they were free from the power of righteouſneſſe, until the precious blood of a God, by the Holy Spirit of Faith, was ſprinkled in their conſciences, that by the pure life or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64389:15"/>love to God and man, they might break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head of ſin, of reigning any longer in them: but on the contrary, they that have no faith given them, in the precious blood of God to clenſe their ſpirits from the power of that Devil ſin in them; their ſins will be their Lord and King, and they muſt periſh together eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally as beforeſaid; Again, by this time it is very clear to you that have the faith of Jeſus, that the Serpent Angel beforeſaid was a ſpiritual body or perſon in the form of a man, before he entred into the womb of <hi>Eve,</hi> by that ſeed or ſon of his called <hi>Cain:</hi> Thus every ſeed or ſpirit by the decree of God, brings forth his own body according to its nature or kind; God the Father being a ſpiritual man from all eternity, in time begot and brought forth himſelf a manchild in mortality, of all pure righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, therefore he was called <hi>the expreſſe Image of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> becauſe he was indeed the very Father, and that made him ſay, <hi>be thought it no robbery to be equal with God;</hi> and that was the cauſe that made him ſay, <hi>that all power was given unto him both in heaven and in earth,</hi> becauſe he knew perfectly that there was no other God but himſelf to poſſeſſe all power; and this made the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to attribute the chief titles of the everlaſting Father, unto the <hi>Son,</hi> that was to be made of a Woman, or of a Virgin; becauſe the Prophet knew very well, that the Father and the Son was but one unſeparable perſon in immortal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from all eternity, and ſo he knew they were to become in time, one unſeparable Perſon of all purity, in mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and I with him know from the ſame ſpirits that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it to the Prophet long before God became fleſh, that that pure mortality, both ſpirit and body that died toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they did both immediately quicken together, a new life in death, or out of death, and they unſeparably, both Father and Son in one perſon, did aſcend together, into that immortal glory that they poſſeſſe together from all Eternity, and ſo they now enjoy it again, in one tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent glorious perſon, both God and man to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64389:15"/>
               <p>This proves the truth of theſe ſayings, <hi>Glorifie me with the ſame glory I had with thee before the world was;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>My glory I will not give to another;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was,</hi> I <hi>am;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that ſaying of God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he bade <hi>Moſes</hi> tell <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that <hi>I am</hi> ſent him; and of that ſaying. <hi>He thought it no robbery to be equal with God;</hi> and of that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I <hi>am the living bread which came down from heaven: if any man eat of this bread he ſhall live for ever;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>This is the bread which cometh down from heaven, that a man may eat thereof and not die;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>For the bread of God is he which cometh down from heaven, and giveth life unto the world;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>I am that bread of life;</hi> Again, Not that any man hath ſeen the Father, ſave he which is of God, he hath ſeen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and of that ſaying, <hi>What and if ye ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before;</hi> and of that full ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that proves Jeſus to be the Father, <hi>He was in the world, and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not;</hi> and of that ſaying, <hi>In the beginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God, the ſame was in the beginning with God, all things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made.</hi> Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is not ſtark blind, by this Scripture muſt needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is no Creator nor Father, but the man Jeſus only, the Lord of life and glorie; and where it is ſaid, <hi>through faith we underſtand that the worlds were fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the word of God, ſo that the things that are viſible</hi> or <hi>ſeen, were not made of things that do appear;</hi> and of that ſaying, I <hi>am Alpha and Omega,</hi> I <hi>am the firſt and the laſt, and behold,</hi> I <hi>create all things new;</hi> and of that ſaying, I <hi>am he that was dead, and an alive, and behold</hi> I <hi>live for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.</hi> This was the man Jeſus that ſate upon the Throne of the Father, with many other Scriptures too tedious to relate, that prove clearly to all that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to eternal glorie, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt that died without the gates of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is the only God, and everlaſting Father, and alone Creator of all things
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64389:16"/>that were made, both in heaven and in earth; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I declare from the Holie Spirit of the Lord Jeſus that ſent us, that whoſoever prayes in his ſpirit or tongue unto any other God or Spirit, but unto my God the man Jeſus, that ſent me, he prayes unto a Devil of his own imagination, inſtead of a God; for that man Jeſus then to come, was <hi>Davids</hi> only God and Saviour: therefore he ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand until</hi> I <hi>make thine enemies thy footstool.</hi> And this Jeſus was all the true Prophets God in the time of the Law, and this Jeſus was the holy Apoſtles God, and all the Chriſtians God in the time of the Apoſtles Commiſſion, or Diſpenſation, or Adminiſtration, that laſted about three hundred years; and this glorious man Jeſus, is my God alone, and the God of all ſpiritual Chriſtians in this laſt age, until he comes in his glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <p n="8">VIII. AGain, but ſome may ſay, if Jeſus Chriſt be the only God and eternal Father, who was that Father that he ſpake ſo much of when he was in mortalitie, where he ſaid, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me; and Father, into thy hands</hi> I <hi>commend my ſpirit,</hi> and ſuch like; To this I anſwer, by Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the Holy Spirit, that <hi>Eliah</hi> ſpoken of in the Law, that was taken up bodily by a VVhirlwind into Heaven, where the likeneſſe of a Chariot and Horſes of fire appeared to <hi>Eliſha</hi> at his departure: I ſay from the Lord, that the body or perſon of that <hi>Eliah</hi> was taken up and glorified in the Heavens by the Creator for that very purpoſe that he might repreſent the perſon of God the Father for that time or ſeaſon, whilſt God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther went that journey in fleſh as aforeſaid: Again, it is written, <hi>he ſhall give his Angels charge over thee;</hi> thoſe Angels were <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Eliah,</hi> who being both glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, they did both repreſent the Perſon of the Father, in the Heavens above the Stars, as they did repreſent the Perſon of the Son and of the Father, when they were in earth beneath the Stars; when <hi>Moſes</hi> was upon this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64389:16"/>earth, he repreſented the Perſon of God the Son that Lamb Jeſus, that was then to come in fleſh; in theſe things, firſt <hi>Moſes</hi> was called the Meekeſt man upon the face of the earth. Again, he was a great Type of Chriſt in this, in offering up himſelf to be blotted out of the Book of Life for the ſalvation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the Lord Jeſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Curſe for his elect <hi>Iſrael;</hi> likewiſe; <hi>Moſes</hi> was a great ſufferer at the hands of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with much patience; as the Lord Jeſus ſuffered with all patience at the hands of his own People or Nation. Again, <hi>Moſes</hi> was made an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Covenant of the Law unto all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the Lord Jeſus was made or became an Angel of the Covenant of Grace or the Goſpel unto all the elect <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever deſpiſed the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was to dye a natural death without mercy; as a Tye of the eternal death of all thoſe that deſpiſe the Grace or Goſpel of Jeſus; and in this he was a great Type of the Lord Jeſus, when he ſaid, <hi>God ſhould raiſe up a Prophet unto you like unto me, him ſhall you hear:</hi> much more might be ſpoken of <hi>Moſes</hi> repreſenting of the Perſon of God the ſon, but I ſuppoſe it is ſufficient for any moderate man. Again, when <hi>Elias</hi> was in this World, he did repreſent the Perſon of God the Father, in theſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt in a God-like manner by commanding fire to come down from Heaven to deſtroy his enemies, and it was ſo again by his commanding like unto a God all the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> that were the National falſe Prieſts to be put to death, for drawing the hearts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the true God, and that was a Type of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal periſhing of all the National Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> in the World at this time; who are Miniſters of the letter on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but call themſelves Miniſters of the Spirit, and yet the Lord Jeſus ſent them not: Theſe are thoſe croaking Frogs that keep the people in darkneſſe, unto whom the people give their ſilver for nought.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Elias</hi> by his asking of <hi>Eliſha</hi> in a God-like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, what he ſhould do for him before he was taken up from him, with his granting of <hi>Eliſha</hi> a double portion of his Spirit, if <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaw his departure from him.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64389:17"/>
               <p>Again, <hi>Eliah</hi> ſpake in the Authority of the Father, when he told King <hi>Ahab</hi> to his face, that it was he, and his Fathers houſe that were the troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by their departing from the living God, with more ſuch like actings of his, after a God-like manner, ſhewing clearly his repreſenting the perſon of God the Father when he was upon this earth; which was but a Type of his repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the perſon of God the Father in the Heavens after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; but ſome may ſay, it ſeems very ſtrange, the Lord having ſo many glorious Angels in his preſence, that he ſhould paſſe them by, and take up a mortal man, or a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſon of God the Father, as beforeſaid: To this I anſwer from the Holy Spirit; all the Counſels of my God the man Jeſus are quite contrary to mans unclean reaſon; yea, and contrary to the pure reaſon of the holy Angels alſo, that God alone may have all the glory, of the revelation of his unſearchable Counſels of wiſdom from his Elect men and Angels. Again, I declare by Revelation from the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the man <hi>Adam</hi> in his Creation, was of the very na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſpirit of Faith, with all divine vertues of pure love, patience, meekneſſe, and ſuch like ſpiritual vertues in his ſpirit or perſon, which were the very ſame divine vertues that lived in the ſpirit or perſon of God his Creator; only in the perſon of God every ſpiritual vertue in him, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite above all meaſure, but in the perſon of the man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> although they were the very ſame heavenly vertues, yet in him they were in meaſure: thus man in his Spirit was created like unto the Creator, of the very ſame Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; only they differed in this, for the body or perſon of God was all ſpiritual or heavenly, not ſubject to mortality; but the body or perſon of the man <hi>Adam</hi> was natural or earthly, ſubject to mortality at the pleaſure of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; for, if the body or perſon of the man <hi>Adam</hi> had been ſpiritual in his creation, as his ſpirit was, then there would have been no difference between the perſon of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and the perſon of the creature: Thus the man <hi>Adam</hi> was made like unto God, a pure natural perſon, of all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64389:17"/>righteouſneſſe in mortality, like unto the ſpiritual perſon perſon of God, which is all righteouſneſſe in glory.</p>
               <p>Again, it is written, the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> of the Earth earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven heavenly: Thus you that ſee by that ſingle Eye of Faith, you may know, that <hi>God</hi> became fleſh or a man, as well as <hi>Adam,</hi> who was called <hi>the Image of God,</hi> becauſe God was a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man from Eternity, as abundantly beforeſaid: Now you muſt underſtand the reaſon why Jeſus the only God was called <hi>the ſecond Adam,</hi> was this; becauſe the body or perſon of the Lord Jeſus was a pure natural body of all righteouſneſſe in mortality, juſt like unto the body or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall; only Chriſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi> had the ſpirit of Faith in him above meaſure, and the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had the ſpirit of Faith in him by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as beforeſaid: again, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> differed from the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> in this, he being made a man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, but the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> knew no ſorrows before his fall; and why did he become a man of ſorrows? it was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the Elect ſeed of the Spirit of Faith overcome in his image the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by the Reprobate Angel-Serpent, as beforeſaid. Again, as for the natures or ſpirits of the holy Angels in their Creation, they were pure Reaſon, quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the nature or ſpirit of Faith in God their Creator; only in their bodies or perſons they were ſpiritual or ſwift of motion, like unto the ſpiritual perſon of God their Creator: but if the nature or ſpirit of the holy Angels had been of of the ſpirit of pure Faith, as they were of pure Reaſon, then there would have been no difference between the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God their Creator, and the perſons of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in their Creation, who are but creatures as well as men; wherefore not the holy Angels, for they are not of the nature of God, as it is written, <hi>he took not upon him the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of Abraham:</hi> but <hi>Elias</hi> as beforeſaid, by the ſecret wiſdom and counſel, and love of God unto man, above Angels, was exalted upon the throne of glory for a moment, to repreſent the perſon of God the Father, and he was made the protector of my God, when
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64389:18"/>God became a child; and it was <hi>Elias</hi> by vertue of his Commiſſion, as a faithful ſpiritual Steward upon the throne of glory, that filled the Lord Jeſus with thoſe great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations of his former glory, that he poſſeſt in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, when he was the immortal Father; and it was <hi>Elias</hi> that ſpake thoſe words from heaven, ſaying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>this is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> hear him again when Chriſt was transfigured upon the Mount, that his garment glittered with the glory of his transfiguration: it was the viſible glorious appearance of the perſons of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> talking with him, that were the inſtrumental Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners of that viſible glory of the Lord Jeſus unto his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, who ſaid, <hi>Maſter, it is good for us to be here:</hi> for that glory was ſo great, that they would have been building of Tabernacles for a continuance in it. Again, I declare from the Lord, that <hi>Elias</hi> by vertue of his Commiſſion did fill E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect men and Angels alſo with Revelation to keep them in obedience until the Lord Jeſus was upon the Throne of his glory again; ſo that when the Lord Jeſus (who was an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute creature, cryed in his agony unto his Father, &amp; when he prayed unto his Father, that that Cup might paſſe from him, if it were poſſible; it being a dreadful Cup for his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent fleſh and blood to drink, he being as ſenſible of pain in his body, as we are in our bodies: and when he cryed out, ſaying, <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and, <hi>Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit:</hi> I ſay again from the Lord, that <hi>Elias</hi> by Commiſſion from this man Jeſus, was that Father that he thus cryed unto in his mortality, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> being then in glory; and the chief ground of all thoſe actions, and ſufferings, and cryings out of the Lord Jeſus in the condition of a creature, unto a Father or a Creator, was to fulfil the Scriptures foretold by his Prophets in the time of the Law: therefore he ſaid, <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs, away, but my word ſhall not paſs away:</hi> again, but you may ſay unto me, did God the third day riſe from the dead by his own power, or by the power of his Deputy <hi>Elias?</hi> to which I anſwer, he by his own decree, and ſpiritual compact with <hi>Elias,</hi> and by that ſpirit of Faith in his innocent body,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64389:18"/>the which Faith died in his pure body, and quickned immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately and brought forth at the appointed time, that natural innocent body out of the grave a pure ſpiritual body, which naturally (at the time appointed) aſcended into glory; for, it was impoſſible for God by death to be held in the grave; becauſe his perſon being pure, his pure ſpirit and death could not remain together, becauſe there was no ſympathy or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement or union between them; yea, they were ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, it was impoſſible for them to be together, except one of them were abſolutely extinguiſhed; wherefore death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too weak, the Lord Jeſus, who is the only God of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted life, brake through death, and hell, and the grave, and through all the ſins of his Elect, by the ſhedding of his moſt precious blood, and ſo entred into his eternal glory, that all thoſe that have Faith in his glorious perſon may be delivered at the appointed time, from ſin, hell, death, and the grave, and enter into eternal glory with him when he comes in the clouds of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Again, the reaſon why mens bodies in death, or after death, do rot or ſtink in the grave, and come to duſt, is, becauſe there was ſin in their bodies whilſt they lived, the which ſin and death had a ſympathy, and as it were a ſweet communion together, whereby death had full power as Lord and King to keep the ſpirits and bodies in the duſt, until the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord of life: but on the contrary, if men had no ſin in their natures or bodies, they might life, and die, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally riſe again, by their own power, in their own time, as the Lord of life did, whoſe body was too pure to ſee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <p>Thus unto you that have Faith in the Lord Jeſus, it is not ſtrange, that <hi>Elias</hi> ſhould repreſent the perſon of God the Father, until the Lord Jeſus aſcended into the right hand of all power and glory of his Father <hi>Elias</hi> again: then when Jeſus was ſet down in the Throne of the glory of the Father again<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Elias</hi> then as a glorified creature, did return all praiſe and glory unto the Lord Jeſus his Creator: ſo that now it is the Lord Jeſus alone, by his holy Spirit, that revealeth all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heavenly wiſdom to elect men and Angels; <hi>Elias</hi> having now with exceeding joy, ſurrendred up his ſpiritual
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64389:19"/>and glorious ſtewardſhip of repreſenting the perſon of God the Father, unto the right owner, and ſole Heir of Heaven, and Earth, and all therein is, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Father, God alone, bleſſed to all eternity: I know I have ſpoken enough to the ſpiritual Chriſtian of this Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <p n="19">IX. AGain, I declare by Revelation from the Holy Spirit, that about this fourteen hundred years there hath not been one true Prophet nor Miniſter, ſent with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Lord Jeſus, to declare, or write, or preach the everlaſting Goſpel of truth and peace unto his Elect: Wherefore I declare (by vertue of my Commiſſion, received by voyce of words from the Lord Jeſus) that all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in this world, whether Prophetical or Miniſterial, with all the worſhip taught by them, whether inviſible or viſible to the people, it is all a lye, and an abomination unto the Lord; both the Miniſtry and their worſhip are as acceptable unto my God, the man Jeſus that ſent me, as the cutting off of a dogs neck. Now unto you that diſcern truth from the Lord, I ſhall give you light into this truth: firſt I declare, that all the true Commiſſionated Prophets of the Lord, in the time of the Law from <hi>Moſes</hi> unto <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> with all the true commiſſionated Apoſtles and Miniſters of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, in the Goſpel, they had every one of them in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion a power given them, to ſet life and death before men, or to declare bleſſing or curſing unto men, which is all one, according to their adminiſtrations received from the Lord. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I declare from the Holy Spirit, that the Lord Ieſus did purpoſe within himſelf, to ſend his Meſſengers three times to the world, &amp; but three times to this bloody unbelieving world, and no more, for a witneſſe or teſtimony unto them, and to make known unto his Elect, that he alone is the only God and everlaſting Father; wherefore you ſhall find it written, <hi>there are three bear record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit, and theſe three are one:</hi> again, it is written, <hi>there are three bear witneſſe in Earth, the Water, the Blood, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and theſe three agree in one.</hi> Again, I declare from the Holy Spirit, that thoſe three in earth are the Lords three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations given to his Prophets or Meſſengers beforeſaid;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64389:19"/>the Water was the Commiſſions of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> under the Law; the Blood was the Commiſſion of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and thoſe Miniſters of the Goſpel choſen by appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Lord; the Spirit, which is the third and laſt Witneſſe, by Commiſſion from the Lord, are thoſe two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> propheſied of by <hi>John</hi> the beloved Diſciple of Ieſus, that were to come in the laſt age, whoſe Meſſage, or Miniſtery, or Propheſie, is all inviſible and ſpiritual, cutting off, or condemning all fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly formal worſhipping of an inviſible ſpiritual perſonal God, taken up by vain-glorious men from the Letter of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which were the Prophets and Apoſtles Commiſſions, becauſe they want a Commiſſion from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Again, I declare from the Holy Spirit, the Lord ſpake by voyce of word, unto his three Commiſſioners that he hath ſent unto the VVorld; yea, I know God the Father ſpake unto <hi>Moſes</hi> as a man ſpeaks unto his friend, as it is written; and I know, that God ſpake unto the Apoſtles in the perſon of the Son, as it is written, becauſe I know the Lord Ieſus ſpake unto me in the perſon of the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit, as beforeſaid; only, the two former Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſaw the perſon of God in part viſibly, but I ſaw the glory of his perſon inviſibly, or within me, becauſe I am the Meſſenger of the Holy inviſible Spirit.</p>
               <p>Again, Concerning thoſe three bearing Record in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven beforeſaid; the meaning of thoſe words are this, God from Heaven, in a three-fold name or title bear witneſſe by Signes and VVonders, unto his three Commiſſioners, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral adminiſtrations given unto them, unto <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets; this perſonal God bare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the name or title of the Father; unto the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles God bare witneſſe in the name or title of the Son; and unto us his third laſt Meſſengers, God beareth witneſſe, in the name or title of the Holy-Spirit, becauſe our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is all ſpiritual, we have to do only with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible ſpirits of men, concerning the eternal eſtates of men and womens perſons, in the great and notable eternal Day of the Lords account; therefore inſtead of natural ſignes upon the bodies or perſons of men and women, as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64389:20"/>in the two former Commſſions of the Prophets and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; the Lord Ieſus beareth witneſſe, that he hath ſent us, by ſpiritual Signs or Wonders, upon the ſpirits of thoſe that are ſealed up through our mouthes, unto eternal life and unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal death, as many do bear witneſſe, whoſe eyes are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at this day in <hi>England,</hi> in this great City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, This is a true teſtimony unto you that have faith in the Lord Ieſus, that he hath ſent us by his Holy Spirit, becauſe there is none upon this earth that beareth witneſſe unto that man Jeſus that was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to be the only God and everlaſting Father, but we only; as <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets and the Apoſtles bare witneſſe in their times unto this Jeſus, to be the only God, and alone eternal Father: but on the contrary, there is hardly a Miniſter in the world that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth an inviſible God, but they preach unto the people ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a God of two Perſons, or a God of three Perſons, that is a Monſter, inſtead of one true perſonal God; or elſe they teach the People to worſhip an infinite Spirit, that is every where, without a Body or Perſon; but he is fain to borrow his creatures bodies to live in; that is a God of words only without any form or ſubſtance, or an infinite nothing, that never can be comprehended nor apprehended in the leaſt by any formed creature, a curſed lying imaginary God from mans own unclean blind reaſon, which occaſioneth all kind of blood and cruelty to be committed in this wicked world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man; for if men underſtood indeed, that there is but one only wiſe God, and that this God is a diſtinct body or perſon, then would men underſtand, that all thoſe that are led by the voyce of the Holy Spirit of God, the man Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, to work righteouſneſſe in their bodies, they lived in, they only ſhall appear with bodies of all righteouſneſſe, like unto their God the man Jeſus, viſibly to behold face to face the glorious body of the God of all Righteouſneſſe for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting world without end.</p>
               <p>Thus it is clear to the underſtanding of all thoſe that are appointed to know the true God, the man Jeſus unto life E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, that there is no true Miniſtry in the World, becauſe they teach not the true God unto the people; therefore as it is written, <hi>they are blind leaders of the blind,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64389:20"/>they muſt needs both fall into the Ditch; Oh! it is an eternal Ditch: Theſe are thoſe Merchants of the Letter of the Scripture, that make the blind Nations their prey; theſe are thoſe ravening Wolves that come in ſheeps cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; theſe are thoſe dumb dogs in ſpiritual things, that bark a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true Prophecy and heavenly revelation that a man d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares by Commiſſion from the Lord Jeſus; theſe are thoſe that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> complained on in his time, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched the people to turn from the ſpiritual Goſpel to the legal form, who began by the Apoſtle in the ſpirit, but were deluded by falſe Hypocrites to be made perfect in the fleſh; theſe were of thoſe Hypocrites that were in Chriſts time, who under pretence of long prayers devour Widows houſes; theſe are thoſe hypocrites that are always teaching of God what he ſhould do for his own glory, when indeed it is their own glory, (in luſting after things that periſh) they deſire, when they thus pray, or preach, or prate; theſe are thoſe bloody hypocrites, and workers of iniquity, that the Lord Jeſus will never own, becauſe he never ſent them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <p n="10">X. AGain, I declare by revelation from the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that there is no Magiſtrate in this world, that bears the name of Chriſtian, that hath any Authority or Commiſſion from the Lord Jeſus to ſet up any viſible form of Worſhip whatſoever, to compel the ſpirits or conſciences of men to how down to his image, that he had ſet up for his own glory, becauſe ever ſince the Lord Jeſus aſcended into his glory, he alone is the Teacher of all his Elect by his Holy Spirit; it is truth, in the time of the Law, before God became fleſh, there were many Magiſtrates and Prieſts commiſſionated from the Lord, to ſet up, and to declare the true Worſhip of God unto all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and it was death by the command of the Lord, if the people deſpiſed to yield o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto it, becauſe it was the Lords Worſhip and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mans worſhip, ſet up from his own lying imagination, that would be a God, but he is a devil; for his creating of a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to deceive the people without a Commiſſion from the Lord, and by taking the prerogative power and glory of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64389:21"/>God to himſelf, who will not give his glory to another, as it is written; therefore in the Revelation, the Dragon there ſpoken of, is the imagination of the Beaſt, and the Beaſt is the body of the Magiſtrate, wherein that Dragon imagination liveth; and the falſe prophet there ſpoken of, is the Magiſtrates Prieſt, and the Image of the Beaſt, is that falſe worſhip ſet up by the imagination of the Magiſtrate, and the ſerpent-counſel of his falſe prophet or Prieſt, to deceive themſelves and the people with them; therefore it is written, <hi>And all that dwell upon the Earth ſhall worſhip him whoſe names are not written in the Book of life, of the Lamb ſlain from the foundation of the World:</hi> that is, all Reprobates, both rich and poor, ſhall bow down unto that falſe, idolatrous worſhip, ſet up by Heathen Magiſtrates, and their Heathen falſe prophets, the National Prieſts, who call themſelves Chriſtian Magiſtrates, and Chriſtian Miniſters, and are blindly called ſo by the people alſo: and yet both of theſe Devils together perſecute with the ſword of ſteel all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Chriſtians under the name or title of Blaſphemers, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, Hereſie, Deceivers of the people, and ſuch like; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpiritual Chriſtian cannot bow down unto that carnal Antichriſtian formal worſhip, ſet up by thoſe carnal Magiſtrates, and their carnal Miniſters beforeſaid, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both lovers of the glory of this world, loving to be honoured as gods, for that curſed heatheniſh idol-worſhip from their own invention ſet up to deceive themſelves and thoſe appointed to damnation with them; wherefore the Dragon Magiſtrate, and the falſe Prophet his Serpent-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that committed ſpiritual fornication together, and all thoſe of their own ſpirits, ſhall every one of them, in the day of the Lords vengeance burn in their ſpirits and bodies together as a lake of fire: thoſe ſpirits and bodies that they ſhall appear with in the Reſurrection, ſhall be that lake of ſpiritual fire and brimſtone, that by the decree of the Lord Jeſus ſhall burn together to all eternity; this is that giving her own blood to drink, who eat up the innocent as bread, and thought they did God good ſervice, in ſhedding of the blood of the Lambs of Jeſus, as their forefathers did; then will theſe Scriptures be fulfilled, <hi>And thoſe mine enemies
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64389:21"/>that would not that</hi> I <hi>ſhould reign over them, bring them and ſlay them before me:</hi> And, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlasting fire;</hi> And the Carcaſſes of the Rebels ſhall be caſt out, where the worm never dies, and the fire never goes out; <hi>And To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is ordained of old for the King;</hi> That <hi>Tophet</hi> is the body of man, and that King is the ſpirit of unclean reaſon in man, <hi>for behold the day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do wickedly ſhall be ſtubble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes, and ye ſhall tread down the wicked; for they ſhall be aſhes under the ſoles of your feet, in the day that I ſhall do this ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; Fill yee up the meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f your Fathers, ye Serpents, ye generation of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; how can ye eſcape the damnation of Hell? for he ſhall have Judgment without mercy that hath ſhewed no mercy; but the fearful, and unbelieving, and the abominable, and Murtherers, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, and Sorcerers, or Aſtrologers, and Idolaters, and all ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, ſhall have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi> Again, the bloody per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors beforeſaid, inſtead of feeding and cloathing the hungry Saint, quite contrary, they do not only take away the food and rayment of the Lord Jeſus, in his Elect innocent Lambs; but they crucifie the Lord of life afreſh, in the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the blood of his Believers, becauſe they yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the ſpiritual Law of faith and love, or command of the Lord Jeſus, either by Prophecying or writing, or ſpeaking the Truth by command from the man Jeſus, who is the only ſpiritual Magiſtrate and Miniſter unto all that are appointed unto eternal glory with him, in that glorious Creation of that new Heaven and new Earth above the ſtars, when this crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beneath the ſtars is utterly deſtroyed, and fitted only for perſecuting Dragon-Serpent-Devils to lament, howl, and weep to all eternity, upon this earth, where the Saints by them were put to grief for a moment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <p n="11">XI. BUt ſome may ſay unto me, do you not allow of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Magiſtrate to govern the rude people? To this I anſwer; The Magiſtrate is very needful in every inhabited Land, for the government of the People in all civil things, to do equal juſtice between man and man: if ſuch a Magiſtrate could
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64389:22"/>be found, it would be a rare thing. Again, I declare from the Holy Spirit, although the Magiſtrate be but a heathen Ruler, as he is; wherefore Chriſt ſaid of this Magiſtrate, unto his Apoſtles, <hi>the Kings or Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip over them, and they that exerciſe Authority upon them, are called Benefactors, but ye ſhall not be ſo; but he that is greateſt among you, let him be as the younger:</hi> yet I ſay from the Lord, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate beareth not the Sword in vain, but he is a type of the true ſpiritual Magiſtrate, that can do nothing but equal Juſtice between the juſt and the unjuſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, all men ought to yield obedience to the civil Laws of the Magiſtrate, either by executing of his Lawes, or patiently by bearing the curſe of the Law upon their own perſons, leaving all vengeance unto God, or elſe they rebel againſt God, and they are in danger of an eternal curſe, becauſe the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this world and the glory thereof belongs only unto the wiſe and prudent heathen Magiſtrates in this Earth, who are the very ſons of <hi>Cain,</hi> that old Serpent-Dragon-Devil, that ſlew his righteous Brother <hi>Abel,</hi> that he and his Seed that are of his own ſpirit, might be the Lords and Rulers of this world for ever; becauſe <hi>Cain</hi> thought, and his dark An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels thinks that there is no world at all, but this only; they have purchaſed the Lordſhip of this periſhing world at a dear rate, for it was the price of the innocent blood of righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> it is their only heaven. Therefore let us that have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived faith to believe in the glorious perſon of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, by his power patiently ſuffer the curſed ſpirit of <hi>Cain</hi> in his heathen Magiſtrates, to ſhed all our innocent blood, if our God will have it ſo, that they may fill up the meaſure of their fathers ſins, from the blood of righteous <hi>Abel</hi> and the holy Prophets, to the precious blood of the Lord Ieſus, and the holy Apoſtles, that our blood that are the two laſt Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Prophets of the Lord Ieſus, may make the laſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of Chriſtians compleat Devils, with their Father <hi>Cain,</hi> who was the firſt bloody perſecutor of the firſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian; therefore it is written, <hi>that Chriſt was a Lamb ſlain from the beginning of the world,</hi> he being ſlain in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Abel.</hi> I ſay from the Lord, by the power of his Holy Spirit, patiently let us yield up our lives with our God, unto
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64389:22"/>thoſe periſhing gods beforeſaid; becauſe we that ſuffer with him are appointed to enter into an eternal Kingdom of glory in another world, hid from the wiſe and prudent Rulers of this vaniſhing world, therefore it is written, <hi>which of the Rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs have believed in him?</hi> again, as it is written, <hi>Why do the heathen then ſo furiouſly rage together, the Kings of the earth ſtand up, and the Rulers take Counſel together, againſt the Lord and againſt his anointed,</hi> or againſt his Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as it is written by <hi>Paul, howbeit, we ſpeak wiſdom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are perfect, yet not the wiſdom of this world, nor of the Princes of this world, that come to nought.</hi> Again, it is written, <hi>which none of the Princes of this world knew; for had they known it they would not have crucified the Lord of glory.</hi> Again, that world that we are to reign in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after we have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, it was purchaſed alſo by blood, but it was the price of the precious unvaluable undefiled blood of our God the man Jeſus, who by his Holy Spirit that ſent us only, maketh us willing to taſte a little of his Cup that he ſo deeply drank of: the ſervant is not greater then the Maſter, becauſe we are to ſit down with him upon his eternal Throne of glory, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his face, in the preſence of all his holy Angels; then theſe Scriptures will be fulfilled, <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſſe ſake, for theirs is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Again, <hi>Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my ſake, rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in Heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which were before you.</hi> Again, <hi>Then ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> Again, <hi>For the Son of man ſhall come in the glory of his Father, with his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and then he ſhall reward every man according to his works.</hi> Again, <hi>Then ſhall the King ſay unto them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world:</hi> Again <hi>then ſhall he ſay unto them on the left hand, Depart from me ye curſed into everlasting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64389:23"/>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <p n="12">XII. AGain, I declare by Revelation from the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that ſince the fall of our firſt Parents, that the ſpirit and body of man are both mortal, and that by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Creator, the ſoul and body of man are both pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created or begot together, and they are both of one nature, and ſo both but one Creature; for it is the inviſible ſpirit that liveth in the ſeed and nature of man, that by the Decree of God creates or begets that form of fleſh in the perſon of a man or woman according to their kind: and thus it is with this whole Creation, every ſeed or ſpirit naturally, by the wiſdom of the Creator brings forth their own bodies or kind, whether Man, Beaſt, Fiſh, or Fowl, and all things elſe that grows, naturally brings forth in their ſeaſon according to their natures: becauſe the Creator by his ſecret Counſel and Wiſdom decreed within his glorious Perſon, before any thing was created or formed by him, that all things or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſhould be created or formed by his infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhould bring forth their own bodies or kind only, and no other for ever: therefore, when men and beaſts ſeeds, are unnaturally mixt together, contrary to their kind the Lord diſcovers them both to their deſtruction, and his glory. Wherefore, I declare from the Lord Jeſus, and it is a curſed Imagination in any man to think when men die, their ſpirits may go into other forms and bodies, contrary to their own natures or kind; as many a curſed lying Atheiſt prates, that denyes the Reſurrection of mens bodies, through the love of ſome dark fleſhly luſt they live in: They are in ſpiritual darkneſſe, underſtanding nothing of the power of God, and ſo erring, not knowing the Scriptures, as it is written, nor the power of God; therefore, it is a common thing for theſe blind Atheiſts in their diſcourſe, to ſay, when men die, their ſpirits may, or do go into a Horſe, or into a Root, or into a Flower, with many more ſuch like curſed expreſſions, they being more ignorant, if it be poſſible, of the Lord Jeſus, through the love of fleſhly pleaſures, then the brute beaſts; therefore they reaſon againſt their own reaſon, and ſay, this Creation or VVorld had never any beginning, nor never ſhall have any ending, two curſed lyes.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64389:23"/>
               <p>Again, They call periſhing nature <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Creator,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God is all things, and all things is God: Thus theſe blaſpheming Devils, liken the incorruptible Spirit of God the man Jeſus, not only u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>to the unclean ſpirit and curſed imagination living in the body of corr pt man, but unto the ſpirits of unclean beaſt, and creeping things, as thoſe Atheiſts in the time of <hi>Paul:</hi> Theſe are thoſe who received the truth to prate of it only, but not in the love of it having pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe, therefore given up to ſtrong deluſions to believe a lie, that they might all the damned, then theſe Scriptures will be fulfilled, <hi>He made all things for his own glory, and the wicked for the day of wrath.</hi> Again, <hi>He ſhall come in flaming fire to render vengeance upon them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hriſt:</hi> Again, <hi>But theſe as natural brute beaſts made to be taken and deſtroyed, ſpeak evil of the things they underſtand not, and ſhall utterly periſh in their own corruption:</hi> Again, <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing eyes full of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſouls, an heart they have exerciſed with covetous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>actiſes, curſed children, which have forſaken the right way and are gone aſtray, following the way of</hi> Balaam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Boſor, <hi>who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe:</hi> Again, <hi>Raging waves of the ſea, foaming out their own ſhame, wandring ſtars, to whom is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the blackneſſe of darkneſſe for ever:</hi> Again, And alſo <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> propheſied of theſe, ſaying, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Lord cometh with ten Thouſands of his Saints, to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute judgment upon all, and to convince all that are ungodly among them of all their ungodly deeds, which they have ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily committed, and of all their hard ſpeeches which ungodly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have ſpoken againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <p n="13">XIII. AGain, Unto you that ſee by the Eye of Faith, from the Lord, I ſhall ſhew you that general Error amongſt men, concerning the ſpirit of man in death; ſome ſay the ſpirit dyeth not at all, but immediately goeth into Heaven or into Hell and the body goes to the duſt only; others ſay, the ſpirit dyeth not, but goeth into another form either of man, or ſome other creature as beforeſaid; others ſay, or think all mens ſpirits go into a Hell or Purgatory when
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64389:24"/>they die for a ſeaſon; others blaſphemouſly ſay, that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of man is God, and that the body only dies and turn to duſt; theſe ſay alſo, God is an infinite Spirit, and all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits came from his Spirit, and ſo return into his ſpirit again; others ſay, the ſpirit and body, or think it turns to duſt for ever: indeed, almoſt all men are in darkneſſe, becauſe they walk by thinking only about things of eternity; but about things that periſh, they think them hardly ever ſure enough unto them: wherefore unto you, whoſe bodies are the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Holy Ghoſt; from the Lord Jeſus, I ſhall declare unto you the truth of this ſecret; you may know, that the ſpirit is nothing at all without a body, and a body is nothing at all without a ſpirit; neither of them can live or have a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without the other: you may know it is the ſpirit only in the body of man, that li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and ſpeaks, and walks, and works, and eats, and drinks, and dies; for the ſpirit is a natural fire of Reaſon, which is that life of light, heat, or motion, that as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re kindleth life and ſtrength through all the fleſh or body of man; only the principal part of the underſtanding of this natural fire of the ſpirit of Reaſon, liveth in the head of man; becauſe that is the glory of the man; ſo that the ſpirit or ſoul is the man, although it cannot poſſibly be without the form or body: wherefore when man dies, and turns to his duſt, it is that natural ſpirit of the fire of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that was the life or ſpirit of the body that dyeth, or is quenched, and goeth out within the body, as fire goeth out in an Oven that is cloſed; ſo doth the ſpirit of man die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his body from all ſenſible life, heart, or motion, until the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible coming of the Lord of life in the Clouds of Heaven at the laſt day: therefore it is written, <hi>Duſt thou art, and unto duſt thou ſhalt return,</hi> when the Lord ſpake thoſe words, he did not ſpeak to the fleſh or outward form or body of the man, but he ſpake to the inward ſpirit or ſoul that underſtands the words of a ſpirit: again, it is written, <hi>in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt dye the death:</hi> that is, if thou through diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to my command, doſt forfeit the image of thy Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, then thou ſhalt ſee mortality or death within thy own body both ſpiritual and natural, and the fear of eternal death alſo. Thus it is clear to you that believe in the Lord Jeſus, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64389:24"/>the ſpirit of man dies and turns to duſt within the body; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing can poſſibly die, but it muſt firſt live; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, nothing can poſſibly quicken or live again, but that which is abſolutely dead, or duſt, or aſleep, void of all motion, heat, life, light, or ſenſe being utterly annihilated to its ſelf, and all other creatures, only being alive in the memory of God, that God alone the man Jeſus might have all the Glory in the new creating of Mankind at the laſt out of duſt, as he had in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of man at the firſt out of duſt, according to that ſaying in the <hi>Revelation; Behold, I create all things new,</hi> in anſwer to that Creation in <hi>Geneſis:</hi> Thus it is with the grain or body of Wheat, except it dies, it never comes to perfection, but abides alone in the duſt for ever: But on the contrary, if the ſpirit of life which is in the body of Wheat doth abſolutely die within its body, then by the decree of God, it quickens out of death unto a new life immediately, and brings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth a glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in due ſeaſon, of many bodies in the ſame form, like unto that which died, of the very ſame nature: Thus it is by the decree of the Lord Jeſus, with the natural ſpirits of all the Elect; firſt they are dead in ſins and Treſpaſſes, before they are capable by the ſpirit or truth to live in righteouſneſs; ſo likewiſe, the ſpirits of men and women muſt be abſolutely dead, when they fall aſleep in the duſt, or elſe they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver capable to riſe again, neither in glory nor in ſhame; ſo that by the decree of God, all life, both ſpiritual and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, muſt firſt enter into death, that through death, or in death, they may quicken a new life of a glorious encreaſe, both ſpiritual and natural; ſo that death in its place is as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Creators raiſing of glory to himſelf as life is in its place; this proves the truth of theſe Scriptures, <hi>He pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out his ſoul unto death:</hi> again, <hi>The ſoul that ſins ſhall die:</hi> again, <hi>He c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yed with a loud voyce, and gave up the ghoſt:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt die the death:</hi> again, <hi>His ſoul was made an offering for ſin:</hi> again, <hi>He was put to death in thy fleſh, and quicked in the ſpirit.</hi> I know I have written enough to ſatisfie (in the proof of this truth) all ſpiritual Chriſtians.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64389:25"/>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <p n="14">XIV. AGain, it is written, <hi>and thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus ſhall riſe firſt;</hi> that is, thoſe that fell aſleep in the believing of the viſible coming of the glorious perſon of the Lord Jeſus in the clouds of Heaven in power and great glory, their bodies ſhall be raiſed firſt out of the ſleep of death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were united by faith unto the perſon of their Lord Jeſus, who was the firſt that ever roſe from the dead by his own power, who raiſed life in death or out of death; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was called the firſt fruits of the reſurrection, or of life from death: again, you that ſee by faith m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y underſtand, that not the ſame bodie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that died or fell aſleep ſhall appear any more at all, then the body of wheat doth as beforeſaid, which <hi>Paul</hi> fitly compareth together in their reſurrection, where it is written, <hi>but God giveth it a body as it pleaſeth him, and to every ſeed his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wn body,</hi> that is as beforeſaid, that grain or body of wheat that died, quickened a new life out of death, and brought forth in a glorious manner in due ſeaſon, many bodies of the ſame form of that that dyed, and yet that body that died appeared no more: ſo likewiſe it ſhall be with all that died in the faith of Jeſus, not the ſame bodies or perſons they lived in, and died in, ſhall appear again any more, but that ſpirit of faith mixt with pure love, and all other ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual vertues, that were in their former bodies, by the which they died unto the power of ſin, and lived unto the power of righteouſneſſe, that divine ſeed of faith ſowed in the former body died with the firſt body, &amp; immediately quickned a new life out of death by the decree of the Lord Jeſus; for you know there is no time now unto God, nor unto them that are dead, and ſo brought forth a ſpiritual body in its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orm like unto that in the duſt; yea of a body of pure righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the ſame nature of that holy ſpiritual faith, that raiſed it out of death; yea, a glorious body, brighter then the Sun in its ſtrength, and as ſwift as thought, yea, bodies of ſuch a bright burning glory, that no perſecuting Canaanites can behold and live, becauſe our ſpirits and bodies according to our faith, and ſhall be made like unto the glorious body of God the man, Jeſus, the which no man in mortality with his natural eye, can behold and live: then ſhall all the Elect in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64389:25"/>the twinkling of an eye, both thoſe that ſlept in the duſt, and thoſe that are alive at that time, whoſe bodies alſo ſhall be changed like unto thoſe that ſlept; then I ſay, they ſhall all aſcend together as one body, to meet their Head, the Lord Jeſus in the Aire; and with their King they ſhall enter into his Kingdom of eternal glory, where that new Heaven and new Earth are beforeſaid, there with holy Angels to behold the glorious face of the only wiſe God, and everlaſting Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, with new glorious ſongs and praiſes unto their Redeemers that was dead, as it is written, to redeem us by his precious blood from eternal death; and now behold be liveth for evermore, therefore we eternally live with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <p n="15">XV. AGain, I declare by revelation from the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that when the Elect are thus glorified, they are abſolutely of the very ſame glorious nature both in ſpirit and body as God is; as God and they were both of one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in mortality, ſin only excepted: wherefore as the ſpirit of faith and love, infinitely in the glorious perſon of God, overfloweth as a fountain, continually with revelation of new Heavenly wiſedom, from whence flows new joys and glory to himſelf, and the holy Angels; ſo ſhall every Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver according to his degree in glory, be as a Well ſpringing up unto everlaſting life, of revelation of new wiſedom, from whence flows new joys and glory within his own perſon, like unto his God; only they ſhall naturally returne the glory and praiſe unto their fountain the Lord Jeſus, for this their exaltation upon the glorious Throne of his own likeneſſe; for it is the righteous actings and ſufferings that was in the innocent body of the Lord Jeſus when the was in mortality, that by his infinite wiſedom is made naturally that glorious fire to kindle new Revelation of Heavenly wiſdom with in his body, for the increaſe of his glory to all eternity as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; ſo likewiſe all thoſe righteous actings and ſufferings for truth ſake, that were acted and ſuffered in our former bodies, by the appointment of our God, ſhall be conveyed into our new ſpritual bodies, that are like unto our God, and ſhall be that glorious fire naturally to kindle revelation of new
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64389:26"/>wiſedom, from whence flows glorious new ſongs and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes unto our Redeemer the fountain of all our glory, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting world without end, as abundantly beforeſaid; then ſhall theſe Scriptures be fulfilled, <hi>to him that overcometh will I grant to ſit with me in my throne, even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in his throne:</hi> Again, <hi>and he that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh and keepeth my words unto the end, to him will I give power over the Nations, and be ſhall rule them with a Rod of iron, as the veſſels of a Potter ſhall they be broken to ſhivers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of my Father; and I will give him the morning star:</hi> Again, <hi>him that overcometh will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God, and he ſhall go no more out, and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the City of my God, which is new</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>which cometh down out of Heaven from my God, and I will write up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him my new name:</hi> Again, <hi>he that overcometh ſhall inherit all things, and</hi> I <hi>will be his God, and he ſhall be my ſon:</hi> Again, <hi>hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth I will not drink of this fruit of the Vine, until that day</hi> I <hi>drink it new with you in my fathers Kingdom:</hi> Again, <hi>and from Jeſus Christ, who is the faithful witneſſe, and the firſt begotten of the dead, and the Prince of the Kings of the Earth:</hi> Unto him that hath loved us, as waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to him be glory and dominion for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <p n="16">XVI. AGain, from the holy Spirit, I ſhall ſhew you the difference between elect men and Angels in glory: the Angels natures or ſpirits being pure Reaſon, they muſt always be ſupplyed by Revelation from the ſpirit of faith in the perſon of God, to keep their ſpirits in pure obedience unto their Creator: but on the contrary, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Spirits being of the very ſame divine nature of God, they are but one voice or ſpirit, ſpeaking all pure obedience within themſelves unto their Redeemer, to whom alone be all Glory and praiſe from my Spirit, with his Elect men and Angels to all eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64389:26"/>
            <head>A Letter preſented unto Alderman <hi>Fouke,</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> from the two Witneſſes and Priſoners of Jeſus Chriſt, in New gate, as an eternal witneſs unto him; with a Declaration unto the Recorder <hi>Steel,</hi> and the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Rowles,</hi> with the whole Bench and Jury; and in general unto all Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Juries in the World. <hi>Iohn Reeve,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> the two laſt Spiritual Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and true Prophets, and only Miniſters of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting goſpel, by Commiſſion from the holy Spirit of the true God, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, God and man, in one Perſon, bleſſed to all Eternity.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>BY vertue of our Commiſſion received by voyce of words from the glorious mouth of the onely true God upon the Throne of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Lord Ieſus Chriſt; we ſhall make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt unto men, what the foundation is of the power of the Civil Magiſtrate, and that he ought not to meddle with ſpiritual things, which God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved himſelf, not allowing any man to touch them upon pain of eternal death, but thoſe onely by him anointed for that purpoſe: Firſt, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that the Scriptures were given by Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit; therefore except the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates were inſpired with the ſame Spirit as thoſe that ſpeak the Scriptures, they ought not to judge any man by them, but ought rather to yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence themſelves unto. Holy Writ, or they muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to eternity. Again, we declare from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64389:27"/>Spirit, that ſince God became fleſh, no Civil Magiſtrate hath any Authority from above to bee the Judge of any mans faith, becauſe it is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual inviſible gift from God, that gives a man aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of everlaſting life; but the Magiſtrates Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is to judge the Civil Lawes of the Land, which is grounded onely upon Reaſon; but the things of Eternity are from God, who is from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Eternity, therefore Faith is the Evidence of things hoped for, and reaſon is judge of things that are viſible: As for you that are skilful in the Law of Reaſon, as ſoon as you hear an Action to be a breach of the Law, you underſtand preſently what puniſhment belongs to the Fact; therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, the Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God for good to them that do well, and a terrour to the evil doer: Again, wee declare from the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that no Magiſtrate by his power from the Law of Reaſon, ought to uſurp the Law of Faith into his Authority, becauſe the Law of Reaſon is utter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ignorant of the Law of Faith, the one being carnal, and the other being ſpiritual; therefore what Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ſoever takes upon him to be the judge of us, who are the Meſſengers of Faith in the true God, they are enemies to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and ſhall ſurely periſh to eternity: Again, from the Lord Jeſus wee forewarn you that are Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, before it is too late, that you tread not in the Lord Mayors ſteps, preſumptuouſly to take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you to judge this Commiſſion of the two edged ſword of God put into our mouths, which if you are left ſo to do, it will cut you in ſunder from the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64389:27"/>preſence of our God to all eternity; for our God is a conſuming fire, who did pronounce us curſed to eternity, had we not obeyed his voyce; therefore we perfectly know who ever is left great or ſmall to ſpeak evil of this Commiſſion, which God hath put unto us, by calling it blaſphemy, deluſion, a devil, or lie, in ſo doing, they have ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and muſt periſh ſoul and body from the preſence of our God, Elect men, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to all eternity; for God hath choſen us two onely, and hath put the two edged ſword of his Spirit into our mouths, as beforeſaid, that whom we are made to pronounce bleſſed, are bleſſed to eternity, and whom we are made to pronounce curſed, are curſed to eternity, and this power no mortal can take out of our hands, neither will out God any more give ſuch power unto men whilſt this World endures: Therefore you that are Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of this Earth, be wiſe and learned and meddle with thoſe things which you know in this World onely, and call not your God to account at your bar; for who ever arraigneth a Prophet at his Judgement Seat, it is all one as arraigning his God, for a Prophet commeth in the name and power of his God; therefore he that deſpiſeth the Prophet, deſpiſeth him that ſent him. Again, we declare from the Lord Jeſus, if any Magiſtrate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be a Preacher of the Goſpel, he having no Commiſſion from our God ſo to do; if he preach any more after we forbid him, then we have full power to pronounce the ſentence of eternal death upon him, and it is ſo unrevocable: Again, we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64389:28"/>declare from the Lord Jeſus, that the cauſe why ſo many Magiſtrates and Miniſters muſt ſuffer the vengeance of eternal death, is becauſe with one conſent they fight againſt the true Meſſengers of God, with the temporal Law inveſted upon them by men: Again, woe would have been unto U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wee had come in our own name; but wee know that God ſent us, as ſure as he ſent <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the Prophets, and the Apoſtles, and that great Authority, as to be Judges of blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt, wee onely are inveſted withal: Wherefore you Magiſtrates that are not yet under this ſentence of eternal death from the Lord Jeſus, our counſel is, if you deſire bleſſedneſs in the life to come, that you would not meddle to be the Judges of ſpiritual things, knowing you have no Commiſſion from the Lord; remember the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>Caiphas</hi> the High Prieſt, if it be poſſible, and prevent the Lord Mayors eternal curſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe 15. of <hi>September,</hi> 1653. you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member by vertue of your Warrant wee were brought before you, not being guilty of the breach of any civil Law, the man Jeſus our onely God, elect men and Angels, will beare us witneſs too: but we being accuſed of words only in relation to a Commiſſion received from our God by voice from Heaven; it was your pleaſure to commit us unto Newgate, as the only offenders in this world, notwithſtanding I gave you a full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Lord Jeſus ſpeaking unto me by voice
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64389:28"/>of words, three morning together, commanding me to deliver this his wonderful and ſtrange meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage unto Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and people, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his bleſſing or curſing them to eternity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their obedience or diſobedience unto this dreadful meſſage of the Lord: and Sir, you may remember that I told you, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſired the Lord Ieſus that I might not be his meſſenger of ſuch ſharp tiding unto men; and but for this my deſire the Lord Ieſus by voyce of words did ſay, that my body ſhould be my hell, and my ſpirit ſhould be the Devil that ſhould torment to eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if I did not obey his command, in declaring his pleaſure unto men: and who was I, poor mortal clay, that I ſhould withſtand the great and glorious Potter of Heaven and Earth, the Lord Ieſus Chriſt my God alone bleſſed to all eternity?</p>
               <p>Again, Sir, You may remember, you did aske us divers queſtions concerning our God, and our anſwer unto ſome of your queſtions were judged as blaſphemy; but we told you that you had no Commiſſion from our God to be the judge of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things, that are eternal in the world to come; but you by Commiſſion from men are the judge of temporal things, onely in this periſhing world: and we onely are the judges, of ſpiritual things, that are eternal in the world to come, by a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Throne of Glory, from the glorious mouth of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Sir, if there were any ſparke of heavenly light ſhining in your underſtanding from the Holy Spirit of Chriſt Ieſus, then you ſhould know in due time
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64389:29"/>that what I have been made to write in this paper, is as true as God is Truth; but now it is too late, your time is paſt, becauſe my God hath no delight in your perſon, therefore he hath left you, as he did King <hi>Saul,</hi> to commit that unpardonable ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, or Spirit that ſent us: Firſt, by your denying the Lord Jeſus to be the only God: Secondly, you may remember, like a curſed Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, God and Man in one perſon bleſſed to eternity, you denyed that ever the eternal God became fleſh, man, or creature, or that God is in the perſon of a man at this time in Heaven or Glory.</p>
               <p>Again, Sir, you may remember when you were queſtioned by us, what your God was; your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, that he is an infinite Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but you could not deſcribe him to be in any eſſential form or perſon: Truly I doe not marvel at your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe you are the ſeed of the Serpent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate Angel that was caſt out of Heaven, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in Chaines of darkneſs or unbeliefe, that you may worſhip a God of words onely, inſtead of the true perſonal God, untill the Judgement of the great Day: my God, the Man Ieſus in glory hath given you your portion already, the penny of this world, your ſoules chiefe delight: make your life that is put a moment as pleaſant as poſſible you can, ſeeing it is all the Heaven you are like to enjoy, as ſure as there is a God.</p>
               <p>Again, Sir, this I know, by revelation from the Holy Spirit, that in the world to come, you ſhall never ſee the glorious face of our God the Man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64389:29"/>Ieſus: becauſe before many Witneſſes you ſaid that God hath no face at all. Sir, once more unto your own perſon, becauſe you have blaſphemed againſt the glorious perſon of our onely wiſe God the Man Ieſus, and againſt the Sacred Scriptures that renders all glory from elect men and Angles to him alone, both in Heaven and in Earth, and againſt the Holy Spirit that ſent us, and for your unjuſt committing of us unto your priſon of Hell, to ſatisfie the malice of curſed accuſers of your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that you might prevent (if it were poſſible) the very purpoſe of God: Wherefore in obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Commiſſion received from the Holy Spirit, from the preſence of our only wiſe God and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the Man Ieſus, elect men and Angels, we pronounce you curſed and dammed ſoul and body to eternity: this is a ſeale unto you from the Lord Ieſus, and a warning unto all perſecuting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; until the great and notable Day of the eternal vengeance of my God, then ſhall your own body by your priſon of Hell, and your Angelical proud and envious ſpirit ſhall be the Divel that ſhall burn within your body more intolerable then any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral fire in this World, and your body ſhall burn more fiery then any natural brimſtone; your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and body being barr'd cloſe priſoners together in utter darkneſs, never ſeeing the face of God, men, or Angels, nor your own face or perſon, for everlaſting, as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
